<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dr. Trigg's secrets, arcana's &amp; panacea's approved by his long admired experience and practice, whereby he wrought such wonderfull cures. With his most experienced secrets particularly appropriated to womens distempers. Now after his death to fulfill his request published as a legacy to his patients. By Eugenius Philanthropos.</title>
            <author>Trigg, William, practicioner of physick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833037</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833037</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37512</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63235)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37512)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2158:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dr. Trigg's secrets, arcana's &amp; panacea's approved by his long admired experience and practice, whereby he wrought such wonderfull cures. With his most experienced secrets particularly appropriated to womens distempers. Now after his death to fulfill his request published as a legacy to his patients. By Eugenius Philanthropos.</title>
                  <author>Trigg, William, practicioner of physick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 112, 127-200 [i.e. 182] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by R.D. for Dixy Page at the Turks Head in Corn-hill near the Royal-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprimatur (*1v) dated: Mart. 25. 1665.</note>
                  <note>With two preliminary contents leaves.</note>
                  <note>Pages 181-182 are misnumbered 190 and 200, respectively.</note>
                  <note>Text and register appear to be continuous despite pagination; catchword at foot of p. 112: A.</note>
                  <note>Tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Botany, Medical --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37512:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Dr. TRIGG'S SECRETS, <hi>Arcana's</hi> &amp; <hi>Panacea's</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Approved by his long admired Experience and Practice, whereby he wrought ſuch wonderfull Cures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With his moſt Experienced Secrets particularly appropriated to</hi> Womens <hi>diſtempers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after death to fulfill his requeſt publiſhed as a Legacy to his PATIENTS.</p>
            <p>By EUGENIUS PHILANTHROPOS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>R. D.</hi> for <hi>Dixy P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge</hi> at the <hi>Turks Head</hi> in Corn-hill near the Royal Exchange. 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:37512:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ex Aed. Lamb. Mart.</hi> 25. 1665.</p>
            <p>G. Stradling. S. T. P. Rever. in Chriſto Pat. D. <hi>Gilb.</hi> Archiepiſcp. <hi>Cant.</hi> à ſac. domeſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37512:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>opus poſthumum</hi> (if it can properly be ſo Epithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed) or if not, I leave to the more curious then uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or profitable Critiks to ſpend their aiery brains about determining; it is out of the Simpathy of <hi>Philanthropos</hi> to the good of Man kind thus preſcribed; and I'le aſsure you it is not <hi>filius ante</hi> but <hi>poſt patrem;</hi> Theſe not imaginary but real Experiments: Their virtue ſuch that mauger all oppoſitions of the <hi>Monopolitan</hi> furies, have run through all the raging billows, and quick-ſands of ſwelling ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity. The Godeſs <hi>Urania</hi> hath far more ſplended Rayes then to be folded up in a skin of Parchment, nor certainly ever can brook any ſuch confinement as to mix the buds of thoſe more ingenious ſpirits who endeavour to approach her Altar; but I wil
<pb facs="tcp:37512:3"/>leave the Explication hereof and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, unto your candid interpretation; the matter herein is made plain, it being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to every intellect, and as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Legacy of the <hi>Authour</hi> to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients freely ſpread amongst them; making good this Adage, <hi>Vox Audita perit; litere ſcripte manent.</hi> So when man ceaſes by vocal advice to communicate any further aſsiſtance to his fellow travellers in this terrene <hi>Stage:</hi> His ſolid Experiments, dipt in this <hi>ſable dye,</hi> which Age nor Envy can never waſte preſerves the benefit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to everlaſting poſterity; So then <hi>Reader</hi> take this and make uſe of it, and as you find the profit, ſo return your reſpects to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your affectionate <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>May 1. 1665.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Turner's</hi> Dentrifices <hi>for the</hi> Teeth, <hi>and his Antidote againſt the</hi> Plague, <hi>and all infectious airs and diſſeaſes;</hi> Eſſex <hi>and</hi> Kentiſh <hi>Agues and</hi> Foggs: <hi>Sold by Mr.</hi> Rooks <hi>at the Lamb and Ink bottle at the Eaſt end of S.</hi> Pauls <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:37512:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <label>A.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>AChes. 52. 63. 129.</item>
                     <item>Ague. 53. 59. 106.</item>
                     <item>Adders ſtinging. 92.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>B.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Bruiſes. 12. 29. 52. 98, 99. 95. 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</item>
                     <item>Difficulty of breathing. 24. 26. 27.</item>
                     <item>Weak Back. 40, 41. 82.</item>
                     <item>Sore Breaſts. 43.</item>
                     <item>Burning. 47. 101. 86. 93.</item>
                     <item>Bliſters. 48. 98:</item>
                     <item>Bleeding at Noſe. 98.</item>
                     <item>Broken Bellies. 77.</item>
                     <item>Barrenneſs. 141.</item>
                     <item>Baldder. 156, 157.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>C.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Catharres. 5. 23. 70.</item>
                     <item>Conſumption. 27. 34, 35, 36. 65.</item>
                     <item>Canker. 28. 69. 73.</item>
                     <item>Cough. 35, 36, 47, 38. 82.</item>
                     <item>Chin cough. 39. 102.</item>
                     <item>Cramp. 52. 108.</item>
                     <item>Chilblanes. 107.</item>
                     <item>Chollick. 77. 95.</item>
                     <item>Convulſions. 81.</item>
                     <item>Choller. 95. 171.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>D</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Drunkenneſs. 8.</item>
                     <item>Drowſineſs. 16.</item>
                     <item>Dropſie. 27. 60. 97. 104. 71, 72.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37512:4"/>
                     <item>Eaſie Delivery. 92.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>E.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Noiſe in the Ears. 20. 93.</item>
                     <item>Ears pained. 21.</item>
                     <item>Sore Eyes. 30, 31, 32. 73. 94.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>F.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Frenzy. 8. 12, 13, 14.</item>
                     <item>Feavers. 14, 15. 164, 165, 166. 168, 169. 170. 173, 174.</item>
                     <item>Flux. 30. 40.</item>
                     <item>Face ſwelled. 44.</item>
                     <item>Fiſtula. 44. 69. 73.</item>
                     <item>Felon. 45.</item>
                     <item>Falling ſickneſs 52, 53. 77. 87. 99. 101.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>G</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Plague in the Guts. 27. 139.</item>
                     <item>Gliſter. 49, 50, 51.</item>
                     <item>Gout. 52. 80.</item>
                     <item>Green ſickneſs. 60. 142, 143, 144, 145, 146, 147.</item>
                     <item>Purge. 81.</item>
                     <item>Piſſing a bed. 148.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>H.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Head, 1. 2, 3, 4. 100. 108.</item>
                     <item>Head-ach. 5. 9. 10. 82.</item>
                     <item>Hypothondriack Melancholy. 7.</item>
                     <item>Heart to comfort. 25. 74.</item>
                     <item>Hectick Feaver. 175.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>I.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch. 48 101, 73. 93.</item>
                     <item>Iaundies. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</item>
                     <item>Impeſtume. 73.</item>
                     <item>Knees ſwelled. 54. 71.</item>
                     <item>Kings Evil. 95.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>L.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Lethargy. 15. 101.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37512:4"/>
                     <item>Liver to open. 27. 60. 67. 99.</item>
                     <item>Lameneſs. 52.</item>
                     <item>Liver to cool. 106.</item>
                     <item>Lungs. 92. 93.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>M.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Maidenheads. 128.</item>
                     <item>Melancholly. 7.</item>
                     <item>Memory. 8.</item>
                     <item>Mouth ſore. 29.</item>
                     <item>Milk to dry up. 43.</item>
                     <item>Mother. 47, 48. 82. 185. 141.</item>
                     <item>Morphew. 108.</item>
                     <item>Megrim. 173.</item>
                     <item>Meaſles. 65.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>N.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sore Nipples. 107.</item>
                     <item>Noſe bleeding. 77.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>O.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Old Sores. 63. 58, 82, 83. 88, 89.</item>
                     <item>Obſtructions. 80.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>P.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Ptiſſick. 26. 90.</item>
                     <item>Piſſing bloud. 29. 109. 161.</item>
                     <item>Pin and Web. 32.</item>
                     <item>Plague. 64, 65. 178., 179, 180.</item>
                     <item>Palſie. 85. 109, 110, 111, 112.</item>
                     <item>Piles. 102. 82, 83.</item>
                     <item>Pluriſee. 80.</item>
                     <item>Pox. 149, 150, 151.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Q.</label>
               <item>Quinzey. 74.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>R.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Rheum. 23.</item>
                     <item>Ringworm. 56.</item>
                     <item>Rickets. 64. 83.</item>
                     <item>Reds to ſtop. 75.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37512:5"/>
                     <item>Running of the Reins. 151, 152, 153.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>S.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sleep looſe. 27. 40. 62. 79.</item>
                     <item>Scurvy. 27. 60. 71.</item>
                     <item>The Stones diſeaſes. 41, 42. 104. 154.</item>
                     <item>Sirrup of Sider. 45.</item>
                     <item>Scalding. 47, 48. 101.</item>
                     <item>Shingles. 48.</item>
                     <item>Sciatica. 48. 57.</item>
                     <item>Swellings. 54.</item>
                     <item>Surfets. 65.</item>
                     <item>Stiches. 80.</item>
                     <item>Stone. 157.</item>
                     <item>Scar. 57.</item>
                     <item>Scald head. 101. 91.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>T.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sore Throat. 160.</item>
                     <item>Termes to provoke. 127. 138.</item>
                     <item>Termes to ſtop. 138.</item>
                     <item>Vertigo. 6. 8. 19.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>V.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Urin to cool. 29. 157. 158.</item>
                     <item>Unguen. aureum. 54.</item>
                     <item>Vomiting bloud. 75.</item>
                     <item>Vomits. 76.</item>
                     <item>Ulcers. 94, 155. 160.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>W.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Whites. 41. 105.</item>
                     <item>Wounds. 62, 63.</item>
                     <item>Wormes. 101.</item>
                     <item>Wind. 81.</item>
                     <item>Womens Privities. 129, 130, 131, 132.</item>
                     <item>Womb. 133, 134, 135, 136, 137.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Y.</label>
               <item>Yard. 156. 159. 161, 162.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37512:5"/>
            <head>Experience is the beſt Miſtreſs.</head>
            <div n="1-52" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Diſeaſes in the Head; and firſt for paine in head through Heat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nternal Medicaments appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to this diſtemper are the diſtilled waters of roſes, of violets, purſlain, water lillies, nightſhade, gourds: <hi>Conſerves</hi> of roſes, violets, citron, water-lilly flowers, ſirrups of the ſame, condited lettice: Of theſe may be framed julips, and potions, as need requires, as for example.</p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of violets, one ounce and a half; barly water ten ounces, oxyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char; half an ounce: mix it for two or three doſes. or</p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of violets, one ounce and a half, of water-lillies and endive, each ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37512:6"/>drams, water of lettice, ſucchory and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive, each two ounces, make it a julip for two doſes; emulſions may be made of the four greater cool ſeeds, poppy and lettice. as</p>
               <p>Take of the four greater cool ſeeds husked half an ounce, of white poppey two drams, barley water half a pound, lettice water three ounces, water-lilly water and roſe water each two ounces, ſyrup of violets, an ounce and a half, mix them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For an Electuary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the Conſerves of violets and roſes, each one ounce, of water lillies and condited lettice, each half an ounce, ſpec. dia marg. frigid, half a dram, with ſirrup of violets, make it an Electuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For outward Medicaments, for hot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers in the head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of violets, roſes and nym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phea, each an ounce, waters of roſes, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and ſengreen, each two ounces, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar half an ounce, make thereof an
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37512:6"/>Epithema to be applied to the forehead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Liniment for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take juice of lettice and plantain, each half an ounce, muſcilage of the ſeeds of fleawort, drawn with lettice water an ounce, oyle of red roſes and water lillies, each one ounce and a half, boyl them till the juice be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and make of it a Liniment for the temples and forehead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnguents are alſo proper for this diſtemper, of which I commend this that follows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of roſes one ounce and an half, of poppy half an ounce, juices of ſengreen &amp; nightſhade, each one ounce, vinegar half an ounce, boyl them till the juices be conſumed, and then adde of white and red ſanders, each half a dram, muſcilage of the ſeeds of flea wort half an ounce, camphire diſſolved in roſewater ſix grains, wax as much as will ſerve to make it an oyntment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of diſtempers in the head, cauſed by cold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a diſeaſe ſprings from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37512:7"/>cauſe, uſe a contrary remedy ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cure, though many medicines wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſympathetically, and effect the cure th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> way, yet more do it by antipathy: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> diſtemper muſt be reſiſted in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and then it may eaſily be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered, but if it reigne long, till it get<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it were an habit, the cure will be pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with great difficulty, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all. Simple medicines conducing he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> unto, are piony roots, gathered th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Moon decreaſing, and the roots of fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, orris, cloves, ariſtolochia, angelic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> white dittany and valerian: And of leave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſe roſemary, marjoram, rue, betony<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſage, hyſop, balme, calamint, organy pennyroyal, primroſes: The flowers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtoechas, are in this much commended which carryeth away black, choller an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> flegme, cleanſeth the brain nerves an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> organs of the ſenſes, reſiſteth all diſeaſe thereof being uſed either in potion, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> decoction, or fomentation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Compoſition for cold diſtempers of the Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take roots of piony and cloves, ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37512:7"/>two drams, marjoram, betony and ſage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach one handfull, flowers of ſtoechas, two pugils, roſemary, lavender, each one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugil, ſeeds of annis and fennel, each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ram, boyl them in a quart of fountain water till a third part be conſumed, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et it three hours in a hot place, and then train it; and adde to the colature of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar three ounces, and clarifie it for a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p, and in the boyling, hang in a cloth of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loves, mace and cinnamon, each half <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dram, nutmeg two ſcruples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Cephalick powder for the Head and Catharres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take nutmegs, cardimoms, cinamon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ignum aloes, each one dram, piony ſeeds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd coriander prepar'd, each two drams, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pecies diambrae, and dia moſco dulcis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach one dram, white amber half a dram; make thereof a powder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Bolus for the Head-ach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the Conſerves of betony and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age, each one ounce, mithridate two ſcruples; make it a Bolus for two doſes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37512:8"/>to be taken at two nights going to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For loſs of Sleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of poppy and nympha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> each one ounce, lettice and purſlain w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, each one ounce and a half, ſpeci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> margarit frigid. half a ſcruple; m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> them, and take it going to bed at twice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Julip for the ſame and to cauſe Reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take violet and lettice water, each one ounce and a half, confect. alkerme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> half a ſcruple, ſirrup of poppy and vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> lets, each half an ounce; mix them fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> one draught.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Vertigo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the Conſerves of lilly co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vally, betony, ſage, roſemary, of each one ounce, of marigolds, half an ounce ſpecies diambrae, diamoſch. dul. each o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> dram, carroway ſeeds, cloves, cubeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>meg, each half a dram, oyle of ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon two drops with ſirrup of ſtoe cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or roſe water and ſugar; make it into a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Electuary, whereof take the quantity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> nutmeg, morning and evening.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37512:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Againſt Melancholly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take diacatholicon an ounce, confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction hamech, a dram and a half, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve it in a ſufficient quantity of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of borrage, balme and harts-tongue, and ſtrain it for one draught.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A potion for the Hypochondriach Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take roots of cichory, borrage, ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zonera, polipody, bark of the roots of capers, each two drams, roots of aſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca one dram, of the leaves of balme, betony, ceterach, fumitory, maidenhair, camedryos, each half a handfull, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taury the leſs, ſea wormwood, each one pugil, of the cordial flowers two pugils, citron pill, two drams, annis and ſennel ſeeds each one dram, ſena, and dodder of time, each three drams, raiſins one ounce infuſe them in a cloſe veſſel, in a hot place, and afterwards boyl them in balneo, to the colature adde of the juices of roſes, borrage, and ſumotery, each four ounces, ſugar one pound; mix
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37512:9"/>them, and make it a cleer drink, whereof take about 4. ounces at a time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An external application for pains in the head, and to cauſe reſt in Phrenſyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two handfulls of dog bryar leaves, four ſpoonfulls of wine vineger, as much breaſt milk, a nutmeg ſheed ſmall, infuſe theſe in a diſh, upon a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing diſh of coals, and apply it to each ſide of the head upon the temples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Vertigo and to reſtore loſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and to comfort the Brain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take eyebright with the flowers, half an ounce, mace prepared with vinegar one dram, coriander prepared 4. ſcruples, betony one ſcruple, cubebs half a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, white ſugar candy ſix drams, make them all into a fine powder, of which take in the morning one dram, upon a piece of bread firſt dipt in maligo wine, or with a poched egge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the Drunken Head-ache.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This too too common diſtemper the Ethicks call a <hi>voluntary madneſs,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37512:9"/>phiſically it's termed <hi>morbus officialis,</hi> an official diſeaſe, it being the office of too much drink to diſturb firſt the Brain and internal ſenſes; and afterwards to leave its dire effects in every member of the body; it obſtructs the <hi>ventricles</hi> of the Brain, with the relaxation and ſoftneſs of the Nerves, cauſed by the aſcention of a multitude of vapours, elevated from the exceſs of meat and drink, or wine and ſtrong drink eſpecially: This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth various effects according to the diverſity of mens natures; of which it is not my purpoſe to treat here, nor to preſcribe Medicines for to encourage Drunkards; ſince in this perverſe Age, Vice is degenerated into Virtue, (I mean it is reputed ſo) it being counted an inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, and ſometimes worſe to refuſe to pledge a health: But I would adviſe all men to beware of this miſcheif, yet if it chance to ſurprize them, uſe this follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Julep.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37512:10"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Drunken Head-ache.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the ſeeds of Cabbages, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, purſlain, each one dram; corian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der prepared half a dram, hartshorn burnt, a dram and an half: Make thereof a fine powder, whereof take one dram in the juice of lemons, oranges, ſirrup or conſerve of quinces or barberryes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or the following Julep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the powder before preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, one dram, ſirrup of citrons, one ounce and an half, of quinces one ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, waters of ſavory and endive, each an ounce and an half; mix them for a Julep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The following Electnary I alſo commend for the ſame diſtemper, and likewiſe good to prevent Drunkenneſs, if you take of it before drinking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Conſerves of roſes, rob of ribes, that is of currans, of barberryes, each half an ounce, of bitter almonds blanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and bruiſed twelve, cabbage ſeeds one dram, red roſes one dram, with the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37512:10"/>ſirrup of water lilies, make them all into the ſorm of an Electuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of a Bruiſe or blow on the Head, or hurt thereof by a fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the cure hereof, have theſe three things alwayes before your eyes: Firſt, endeavour to mitigate the pain: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to hinder apoſtemation; and thirdly, if there be a wound, to have a care to the cure of it; and regulate the patient by due order of dyet: If there be repletion in the body, then opening of a vein is convenient; but if age and ſtrength will not admit of that, then have erecourſe to the uſe of Cliſters; to prevent an infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation by evacuation of the humours that way. as,</p>
               <p>Take Pellitory, mercury, centory the leſs, with the flowers, ſena half a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; boyl them in fountain water, and in half a pint of the decoction diſſolve half an ounce of the Electuary, called <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicta laxativa,</hi> two drams of oyle of roſes, and a little ſalt, and give it for a Cliſter.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37512:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a diſcuſsing and digeſting plaiſter for the Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Camonile, melilot, ſouthern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, and marjoram, each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, red roſes dryed, wheat bran, meal of beans, lupines &amp; barley; each half an ounce, mirtles and cipreſs nuts, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber fifteen, or for want thereof, two drams of balauſtins, bruiſe what is to be bruiſed, and boyl them with their juice, till the hearbs be ſoft, then work them together in a mortar, till they come to the forme of a Cerote, to which in the end adde a little oyle of camomile and dill; then beat it again and apply it hot to the place affected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eor he Phrenſy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This affection ſometimes followeth a Feaver, and it ſometimes is in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Brain: For the cure it is good to uſe frictions and ligatures to the extremityes, to hinder the aſcention of the humours: Lotions are likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be uſed to the Feet.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37512:11"/>
               <p>There muſt be alſo uſed in this caſe, both Cliſters and Bloud letting; though not by admittance, yet by compulſion; and the Cliſter muſt be held in with a cloth, and to be repeated after bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A good Cliſter for the Phrenſy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Mallows, and marſh mallows, both herbs and roots, pellitory, mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ſena, each one handfull, barley one pugil, five prunes, manna half an ounce, ſeeds of gourds and ſennel, each one dram; decoct them all in a ſufficient quantity of water, and in the Colature diſſolve in it half a pint, of diacaſſia half an ounce, benedict. laxativa three drams, ſolutive ſirrup of roſes three ſpoonfulls, oyle of violets one ounce and an half, the yolk of one egge; mix them for a Cliſter to be injected at any time: Then on the next day after bloud letting, uſe this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xative.</p>
               <p>Take ſolutive ſirrup of roſes ſimple, two ounces, ſirrup of villets ſix drams,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37512:12"/>borrage water one ounce, lettice and anniſeed water, each one ounce and a half; mix them for a potion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Apozeme for the Region of the forehead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take leaves of Lettice, plantain and vervain, of each an handfull, roſes and violets, each two pugils, red ſaunders two drams, ſeeds of plantain and ſorel, each two drams, ſix poppy heads; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct them in equall parts of water and wine vinegar, wherein dip linnen clothes or a ſpunge, and apply it to the region of the forchead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another frontal for the Forehead in the Phrenſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the diſtilled waters of red Roſes, lettice, vervain, betony and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lillies, each two ounces, of plantain and nightſhade water, each one ounce, of juice of purſlain and ſengreen, each one ounce and an half, wine vinegar one ounce; mix them, and therein dip warm linnen clothes and apply it to the forehead: <hi>This is ſingular good fo ſuch
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37512:12"/>as are diſtracted with raging Feavers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Lethagy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the <hi>prodromus,</hi> or forerunner of the Appoplexie, and conſequently of death it ſelf: For cure hereof <hi>Caſtoreum</hi> is much commended to be given in drink with Oxymel: or thus,</p>
               <p>Take of Caſtoreum, two ſcruples, mace one ſcruple; powder them very fine, and give this powder in betony water, and ſirrup of citrons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An excellent ſecret for the Lethargy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the conſerves of Roſemary flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and primroſes, each half an ounce, of roſes three drams, of aromaticum ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatum, one dram, <hi>laetificans Galeni,</hi> half a dram, with ſirrup of Stoechas, and juice of citrons; reduce them into the forme of an Opiat; whereof may be given, the quantity of a nutmeg at a time.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37512:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An excellent Powder to be uſed againſt the diſeaſe called <hi>Caros,</hi> which is exceſsive drouſineſs, and profound ſleepineſs, which ſtupifies the ſenſes, and hurts the action of the principal parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many have I known ſo ſubject to this diſtemper, that at all times and in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whereſoever they have ſate down they have fallen aſleep, but for remedy of his evil.</p>
               <p>Take Nutmegs, mace, galanga, each two drams, citron pill, cinnamon, the true coſtus, of each one dram, the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of ſtoechas, roſes, roſemary and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, each one dram and a half, ſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanth, ſpike and lavender, each half <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dram, Caſtoreum one ſcruple; bruiſe them into a roſs powder, and in a fine linnen bag, apply them to the <hi>Corona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sutor,</hi> which is that which women call the mold of the head; if it be ſewed, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quilted in a fine cloth, the patient may wear it at any time either at home o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abroad under a Cap.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37512:13"/>
               <p>Having now preſcribed a remedy for <hi>too much ſleeping;</hi> I have provided helps for them alſo, who are ſubject to <hi>too much watchings,</hi> how they may procure ſleep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pills to cauſe Sleep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take <hi>ſpecies diambrae</hi> two ſcruples, <hi>diamorſc. dul.</hi> half a dram, white amber one ſcruple, ambergreaſe three grains; mix them, and with ſirrup of citron pills, make four and twenty pills thereof, whereof let the patient take three, going to bed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame intention, I commend the following Electuary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the Conſerve of water Lillies half an ounce, <hi>ſtyrax Calamita</hi> one ſcruple, pearls prepared two ſcruples, ambergreaſe and musk, each one grain; with ſirrup of violets; make them a mixture, which may be reſerved in a glaſs for your uſe, when occaſion requires, taking the quantity of an hazel nut.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37512:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Decoction profitable for the ſame intention, eſpecially where too much watching have cauſed a diſtillation of Rheume upon the Lungs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two Dates, three heads of white Poppy; make a decoction there of in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſufficient quantity of Lettice water to three ounces, then ſtrain it, and diſſolve in the Colature half an ounce of ſugar o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> roſes; which give for a potion whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> need requires.</p>
               <p>Obſerve alwayes in theſe kind of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, theſe remedies are not to be exhibited, before the humour be eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuated by purgations; eſpecially if the affect be with matter, and much vapours are aſcended to the head, which as there be diverſity of cauſes which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure diſtempers to the head, ſo there is needfull various kinds of purgations, as the diverſity of the cauſe requries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Hypochondriac Melancholly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of Fumotery half an ounce, of endive and betony two drams, juice of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37512:14"/>citrons one ſpoonfull, waters of cichory, dodder and ſumotery, each one ounce, and a little cinnamon water; which mix for a potion, and uſe it as often as occaſion requires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Vertigo Firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake this purging Bolus, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of Diacaſſia three drams, <hi>hiera pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ra</hi> two drams, rhabarb in fine powder one ſcruple; make it into a Bolus with a little ſugar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then uſe the following Electuary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the vapours from the Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the conſerve of piony flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, half an ounce, conſerve of marjoram one ounce, of roſes two ounces, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melad of quinces one ounce, citron pill half an ounce, one mirobalan embelic, half an ounce of rob de ribes, coriander prepared one dram, fennel ſeeds anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds and piony roots, each half a dram, red coral one dram, Maſtich one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with ſirrup of citrons make it an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37512:15"/>Electuary, whereof take the quantity of a nutmeg after ſupper and dinner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſinging and noiſe in the ears, which cauſeth deafneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take white Hellebore, Caſtoreum, each two drams, coſtus a dram and an half, rue and marjoram, each one dram, bitter almonds five drams, Euphorbium half a dram; let them be bruiſed and boyled in wine over a gentle fire an hour, then ſtrain it and drop thereof into the ears; and let the patient receive the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour of this decoction, into the ears. or</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For noiſe in the Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of Bayes three ounces, ſtrong vinegar one ounce and a half, Caſtoreum in powder half an ounce, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niper berryes one dram and an half; let them boyl in a cloſe veſſel till the vine gar be conſumed, then ſtrain it through a cloth, and drop of it into the ears; but in all adminiſtrations to theſe parts, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his rule.</p>
               <p>Never admit above three or 4. drops
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37512:15"/>at a time of any medicine to be applyed into the ears, for a great quantity eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of any oleaginous matter is hurtfull; therefore alwayes let your applications be very liquid that they may the eaſier paſs in and out, and not ſtick within to offend the head; and apply all things warm only, neither hot nor quite cold, and alwayes when you uſe any new me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine or dreſſing, be ſure to cleanſe the parts well that no filth remain of the old.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For grievous pains in the Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Warme new Milk is good to be drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into the Ears, ſo is the white of an egge, being beat firſt into an oyle o li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and the oyle of ſweet almonds, and the oyle of the ſeeds of white poppy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Compoſition for pain in the Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of new Breſt Milk if it can be had, two ounces of the whites of eggs beaten half an ounce, gooſe greaſe a dram; mix and work them together and drop into the ear, a drop or two at a time warme; oyle of earth wormes is very
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37512:16"/>profitable for this grief, a drop or two thereof being dropped into the Ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame, an excellent experiment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a great Onion, and make it hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and put therein of Caſtoreum and Euphorbium, each half a ſcruple, opium ſix grains, and fill it up with oyle of bitter almonds, oyle of dill, or ſuch like; and roſt it under the embers; then preſs out the juice and ſtrain it; and uſe it a drop or two at a time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Catharre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The defluction of humours, from the head to the inferiour parts, is generally called a Catharre. Thoſe that would be acquainted with it; let them contrary to their uſe, but go wet and cold in their heads and feet, &amp; they may quickly have a companion that they cannot be ſo ſoon rid of again: It is uſually the forerunner of a Conſumption, deſtroying the lungs by the diſtillation of humours, like as rain dropping into an houſe through the roof, rots the wood and timber and whatever it falls upon within.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:37512:16"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cleanſe and evacuate the humour in a Catharre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the whiteſt Agarick half a dram, of rhabarb a dram, manna a half an ounce, ginger a ſcruple and a half, diagry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium three grains; bruiſe and infuſe them all in waters of annis and fennel, each three ounces; boyle it gently, and ſtrain it, and in 4. ounces of the liquor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve two ſpoonfulls of ſolutive ſirrup of roſes, and one ſpoonfull of cinnamon water, and give it the patient warme in the morning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pills to ſuppreſs the Rheume.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the maſs of pills Cochie and Maſtichine, each one ſcruple, Agarick trochſcated a ſcruple and a half, Trochis alhandali 4. ſcruples, with the infuſion of gum dragon in cinnamon water; make it into pills and rowle them in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of lignum aloes, and take one at a time, uſing them often; and that the matter may be driven downwards from the ſuperiour parts, take a ſcruple of theſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37512:17"/>pills going to bed, or more or leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the condition of the patient; and in the morning take as much more, drinking after in a draught of Maligo wine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſtoppings of the Breaſt and difficulty of Breathing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Licorice half an ounce, elecam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane five drams, raiſins ſtoned, and fat figs, each one ounce, jujubes half an ounce; make of theſe a decoction in the waters of ſcabious and hyſſop, each half a pound, flowers of the ſloe-tree, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeed, each three ounces; in ſeaven ounces of ſtrained liquor diſſolve of manna five drams, and adde to it a ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of cinnamon water, ſtrain it all through a linnen cloth, and let the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient take half of it in the morning faſting, and the remainder the day following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Drink to ſtrengthen the Heart and reſiſt Poyſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Cinnamon two drams, cloves, nutmegs, mace,<gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>grains, cardamoms,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37512:17"/>each one dram, zeadoary three drams, citron pills, galanga cubebs, long pepper, each half a dram; bruiſe them groſly, and infuſe them 24. hours in a linnen bag, in two quarts of the beſt wine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one pound of pure fine ſugar, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of let the patient drink every day a draught before dinner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For trembling of the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the five opening roots, each half an ounce, cichory one ounce, bark of Tamariske &amp; citron pills, each one dram and an half, tops of wormwood, cardus benedict. ſage, each one handfull, of the cordial flowers, each one dram; bruiſe them and infuſe them in wine, and drink of it as occaſion requires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A cordial Electuary to comfort the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two handfulls of Borrage leaves, as much bugloſs, one handfull of endive, roſemary, time, ſavory, hyſſop, each half an handfull; boyle theſe in three pints of fair water till half be conſumed, then ſtrain it, and adde one pound and an half
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37512:18"/>of ſine ſugar, a few cloves, half an ounce of cinnamon, and a quarter of an ounce of ginger finely beaten; then to boyl it to the thickneſs of honey, and take as much as a hazel nut in a morning when need requires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Ptiſick an approved ſecret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pint of Honey and put to it an ounce of flower of licoris, a quarter of a pound of currans bruiſed, an ounce of ſweet fennel ſeeds bruiſed, and a dram of the flower of elecampane; ſtir all theſe together over the fire into the honey, and ſo reſerve it for uſe, taking the quantity of a nut at a time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An opening Drink, helping ſhortneſ of Breath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two quarts of running water, put into it two handfulls of unſet hyſſop, and tops of roſemary, ſcabious, lung wort and maidenhair, each a handfull, 10. figs ſliced, a root or two of elecampane; boyl it to a quart, and ſweeten it with ſugar candy, and drink it as occaſion requires.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:37512:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Diet drink to cleanſe the bloud, open the Liver and Spleen, and is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent againſt the Scurvy, Dropſie and Conſumptions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Egrimony, ſpeed well, liverwort, ſcurvy graſs, water creſſes, each a good handfull, of monks rhabarb and red mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, half a pound, horſe radiſh, liquorice, ſaſſafras, each 4. ounces, ſena 7. ounces, ſweet fenel ſeeds an ounce, 4. nutmegs; pick and waſh the herbs and roots and bruiſe them, and put them in a bag in three gallons of Ale, letting it work in the Ale, and at 4. dayes old drink a pint of it every morning, and at 4. in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An excellent potion for the Plague in the Guts, and all Feavers and diſtempers of Melancholly and aduſt Choler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Sena 6. drams, rhabarb two drams, cremor tartari half a dram, ſweet fennel ſeeds a dram, a little cinnamon, infuſe them all night in half a pint of white wine, in the morning ſet it on the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37512:19"/>fire till a boyl, and then ſtrain it, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve in it over the fire an ounce of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, then ſtrain it again, and adde to it an ounce of ſolutive ſirrup of roſes, and ſo drink it, and about two hours after drink ſome thin broth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Canker, or any heat in the Mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of red Sage and Rue, each an handfull, of ſorel and groundſel, each half an handfull, cut the herbs ſmall and ſtamp them in a wooden mortar, then take roach allom the quantity of a wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut, white coperas as much as a hazel nut, and burn them together, take alſo as much coperas and allom unburnt, ſtamp this with the herbs very ſmall, then boyl them in a pint of running water, with three ſpoonfulls of Engliſh hony, till half be conſumed, then let it run through a ſtrainer into an earthen veſlel. when it is cold put it in a glaſs, and when you uſe it you muſt gargle with it hot 3. times aday; you may lay ſome of the herbs that remain in the ſtrainor to the foreſt places if you ſee cauſe.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37512:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the htat of the Vrin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the rinds of Hazel, ſleep them in ale or beer, and drink it for your firſt and laſt draught every day and at any other time of you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Diſtill Purſlain in a common ſtill, and drink of that water a quarter of a pint e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning, ſweetned with white ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar candy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Strain cauſing one of ſpet bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pint of good Sack, and ſet it on the fire, and put into it a good piece of fine ſugar, let it ſo ſtand till it be ready to burn, (burn it not) then brue into it the yolks of 4. new laid eggs, ſtrain it (bruing it continually till it be like a caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, then drink a draught thereof firſt and laſt both morning and night: Sirrup of Comphrey is likewiſe very good for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another for a Strain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The powder of Corral and powder of rock amber beads, each half a dram,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37512:20"/>make them up into paſt with a little gum dragon, conſerve of red roſes; this you muſt eat morning and evening, and be ware of violent ſtirring, wine, women, and meats with pepper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Flux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Put one ounce of whole Pepper into a quart of new milk, boyl it unto a pint, and drink half a pint thereof every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and faſt three hours after it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Pin or Web, or any other Rheum in the Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two new laid Eggs, make a hole in the crowns, put the whites, into a ſawcer, then put away the yolks, and take one of the ſhells and waſh it with fair water, and put half the white into it, then put in as much white coperas as a peace, and ſo much roch allome, then fill the egſhell up with the reſt of the white, the hole of the crown of the egge muſt be no bigger then a two pence, that you may put it up with a little white dow, then wrap it in wet paper, and rake it up in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37512:20"/>warm embers till it be very hard, (and if it be an hour in roſting it is the better) then ſtrain it very hard through a ſtrong cloth, drop one drop of this water into your eye lying on your back, morning and night, and alſo at 4. of the clock if need be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another for the Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of Hogs greaſe very new 2. oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſteep it in roſe water ſix hours, then waſh it twelve ſeveral times in good-whitewine, wherein <hi>lapis caluminaris</hi> hath been quenched 11. times, let the greaſe ſleep ſix hours in the laſt of the wine, then take Tutia well prepar'd and finely powder'd one ounce, of the ſtone Hematitis well waſhed a ſcruple, of aloes well waſhed and made into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der twelve grains, powder of pearle three grains; mix all this in your greaſe with a little fennel water, till it come to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſalve, put as much as an ordinary pins head, into the corners of both eyes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37512:21"/>next the noſe, and anoint the eyelids therewith when you are in bed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Rheume in the Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take white Archangel flowers, and put them into ſallet oyle, and heat them upon a chaſing diſh with coals, and lay them to the nape of the neck as hot as you can ſuffer them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For blear'd and watry Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a quarter of a pint of the pureſt running water, and put it into a vial of glaſs, and put thereto 2. drams of the beſt white coperas, being firſt beaten into very fine powder, then put thereto three or 4. ſpoonfulls of red fennel water, (or for want thereof as many of the neweſt ſprigs of red fennel growing next the root) this being done lute up your vial cloſe, and ſet it in a skillet of fair water and warme it ſo till it begin to boyle, then take it out and ſo keep it for your uſe, let the patient morning and evening have a drop dropped into the eye.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37512:21"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a pin or Web in the Eye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Nightſhade, Balme, red nettles and vervain, each a like quantity, and a good handfull of bay ſalt, and beat them altogether, and if the right eye be ſore, lay it to the left wriſt, and ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; If you make it in May or June, it will keep all the year.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Heat in the Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the white of a new laid Egge, beat it very well, then let it ſtand and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and take a ſpoonfull of the cleareſt thereof and as much breaſt milk, and ſo much red roſe water as both of them, mingle them together, put them into a glaſs, and when you uſe it, warme a little thereof bloud warme, and dip two rags (folded three or four times double) being very fine and bind on the eyes when you go to bed, and in the day time waſh therewith your eyes as often as you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Water for ſore Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſix drams of Tutty, made into
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37512:22"/>fine powder, as much aloes in powder, as much fine ſugar, a pint and a half o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whitewine, as much white roſe water put all theſe into a pottle glaſs, ſtop it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cloſe and ſun it a month, ſhaking it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well twice or thrice a day and ſo keep i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for your uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Electuary for a Conſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Elecampane roots one pound waſh and ſcrape them clean, cut them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> little ſquare pieces, then take of radiſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one quarter of a pound, ſlice them thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and as many wardens as the weight o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both theſe, ſlice them thin likewſie, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them altogether laying them in laine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in a pipkin, and put between every lain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of them ſome honey, lute up the pipki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cloſe with paſt, bake it in an oven with houſhold bread.</p>
               <p>A pint of Honey may be enough for this, when it is cold beat it to a pulp, in a ſtone mortar, and take it at night an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mornings as an Electuary.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:37512:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Julip for a Conſumption, or any weak body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a Capon that is fleſhy and not fat, dreſs him clean, cnt him into about ten pieces, waſh him in white wine, cut every piece by it ſelf, put into every piece a ſmall skewer that the fleſh may not touch the bottome, then put them into a jugge with a narrow mouth that will hold three pints or a pottle, then put to it twenty raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, 4. dates quartered, two large maces, a ſprig of roſemary, ſtop it up cloſe with a cork, then lute it with paſte and tye a cloth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that alſo, that no aire get in, then ſet the jugg in a pottle of water, &amp; ſet bricks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it that it may not ſtir, ſo let it boil ſix hours at the leaſt, keep the pot full of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the neck of the jug, which may be done by having other water ready heated to fillit, then take it out of the pot, and when it hath cooled half an hour pour out the julip, if there be any fat in the top, take it off, put to this ten grains of amber
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37512:23"/>greaſe in powder ſtir them together, and ſo put it up in your glaſs, and take three ſpoonfulls of this at a time, warme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when you go to bed, if the patient be to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hot, put leſs or leave quite out the ambe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An electuary for the Conſumption of the Lungs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pint of Hony, ſet it on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fire and skim it clear, put thereto two or three ounces of ſearc'd licoris, as much anniſeeds well dryed, half a grain o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long pepper, the lungs of a Fox beate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſearc'd, two or three leaves of Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> foor cut like Tobacco, and a quarter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an ounce of the root of burdock, boil th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> till it grow ſomewhat gluttinous, tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hereof (on a knives point) morning an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> night, in your bed and other times yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſe, letting it go leiſurely down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Cough or ſhortneſs of breathing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a quart of running water, boyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therein a handfull of unſet Hyſſop, till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come to a pint, ſtrain it and put thereto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:37512:23"/>quarter of an ounce of licorice ſliced, half a handfull of raiſins of the ſun ſliced, two figs, two dates, ſweet-fennel ſeeds and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds half an ounce, boyl theſe till al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt half be conſumed, then let it run through a ſtrainer and ſweeten the liquor with white ſugar candy to your liking, ſo drink of it four ſpoonfulls at a time bloud-warm, in the morning a quarter of an hour before you riſe, and at night when you are in bed lie on your back and let it go leiſurely down.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Sirrup for a Conſumption and the Cough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two hanefulls of Elecampane, ſlice it thin, boyl it in fair water half an hour, ſhifting it two or three times, then take two or three handfuls of coltsfoot, two or three hand fulls of liverwort, one of hartstongue, and two handfulls of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gremony, one of maidenhair, a quarter of a handfull of maiden hyſſop, an ounce of China roots ſliced, two ounces of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corice ſliced, a ſpoonfull of anniſeeds, a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37512:24"/>good handfull of raiſins of the ſun ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, 4. or 5. figs ſliced, two ſpoonfulls of French barley bruiſed, and boiled in two or three ſeveral waters; put all theſe into a pottle of running water, boi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them untill more then half be conſumed, and ſtrain the liquor from the drugs, and put in your elcampane boiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and a pound and a half of ſugar, boil it to a ſirrup and keep it in a galley pot for your uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another for the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nettle ſeed and Elecampane dried and beaten ſmall, and make them into an Electuary with honey, and give the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient every morning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A China broth for the Conſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take three quarts of fair running wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, put it in a pipkin and ſet it over the fire till it be ready to ſeeth, then take it off and put into it a ſmall handfull of China and another of Saſſafras chips then stop it up cloſe, and let it infuſe upon em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers 24. hours, then take a middle ſized
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37512:24"/>Cock chicken, and flea off the skin, and cut it open in the back and take out the garbage, and beat it with a peſtle, let it touch no water but put it into the China liquor and put to it ſix or ſeven leaves of colts foot and a little maidenhair, thirty raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, and a little ſtick of mace, then let theſe boyl together till half be conſumed, let it be ſtrained again very hard, ſet it on the fire, boyl it and skim it again, make it ſweet with ſugar and lemons, or ſower, as rhe patient likes it, and let him take of this a good draught morning and evening, and at four of the clocke in the afternon if he pleaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Chin Cough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a handfull of Rue, and ſtamp it, then mingle it with Engliſh honey and make it into a kind of Conſerve, give it mornings and evenings, and afternoons and nights to bedward, as much at a time as a damoſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Roaſt an Egge rare, dreſs it and put as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37512:25"/>much flower of brimſtone into it, as will lie upon a twopence, mix it well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and let the patient ſup it every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Broth for the Spleen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of Couch or graſs roots, ſucco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry roots and fennel roots, of each half an ounce, of the bark of caper, and bark of tamarisk, each two drams, currans and capers (waſhed from the ſalt) each three drams, boyl theſe in the belly of a chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a branch of time and put in the bottome of a white loaf in the boiling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Flux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take bark of an Oak from the tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, grind it to powder and ſearce it, put it into new milk and byl them very well together, eat of this pap every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and what other time you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another being alſo good for a weak back.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Bread that hath been baked half a year at the leaſt, grate it, put it into a quart of new milk with a good ſtick of cinnamon, and a good piece of iſinglaſs,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37512:25"/>boyl it to a pint, and thereof morning and evening you may eat what you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a weak back or the whites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take an ounce of Cinnamon, one ounce of white comphrey roots, one ounce of polipodium of the oke, three ounces of white ſugar candy, make all theſe into powders, then mingle them together, and take ſo much at a time thereof as will lie upon a ſixpenny piece, every morning for the ſpace of five dayes, and ſo likewiſe in the afternoon, and drink a draught of red wine an hour after every taking, this may be taken longer if there be cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Plaiſter for ſwelling of the Stones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pretty quantity of Cows dung, and ſeeth the ſame in milk, then make a plaiſter thereof, and lay it meetly hot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſwelling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Comminſeed, Anniſeed and Fenegreek, of each a like portion, ſeeth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37512:26"/>them in ale, and ſtamp them, and temper them with freſh <hi>May</hi> butter, or a little oyle of olive, and ſo apply it to the ſore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another for ſwelling in the Stones in the beginning of the grief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there be much inflammation in the Cods, you may make an ointment of plantain the white, the yolk of an egge, and apply it to the grief twice or thrice in a day, when the pain is intollerable and the party of good age, and of a ſtrong complexion, (if the premiſes will not help) make a plaiſter after this ſort, viz.</p>
               <p>Take Henbane leaves a good handfull, mallow leaves a handfull and a half, ſeeth them well in clear water, then ſtamp them and ſtir them, and with a little of the broth, bean flower, barley flower, oyle of roſes and camomile ſufficient, make it up, and put it on the ſwelling lukewarme, henbane is good as <hi>Avicen</hi> ſaith, to diſſolve the hardneſs of the Stones by a ſecret quality.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37512:26"/>
               <p>Take new Milk and white bread, grate it mallows and red roſe leaves, of each a handfull, then chop them and boil them together, till it be thick, then put in honey and common turpentine, ſpread it on a cloth and apply it to the ſore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a quart of fair water half a pint, of oatmeal, two handfulls of ſmalledge, half a handfull of red nettles, boil all theſe well together being firſt chopt, and put in about a quarter of a pound of ſheeps ſuet minced, ſtir them well on the fire, and apply part thereof as hot as the patient can ſuffer it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For an Ague in the Breaſt, as alſo to dry up the Milk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take good Aquavite, linſeed oyle, warm them in a diſh upon a chafingdiſh with coals, dip therein two cloths cut fit for the Breaſts, and lay them on the Breaſts, as hot as can be endured; lay alſo a little lump of flax two under each arme,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37512:27"/>being well dryed and warme, and ſo dreſs the Breaſts therewith both morning and evening.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Swel'd Face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Roſemary leaves mince them, boil them with milk and oatmeal to a pultice, then put thereto a ſpoonfull of honey, apply it as oft as there is cauſe, and as hot as the patient can ſuffer it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For any ordinary Soreneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pint of Ale yeſt, as much groundſel as comes to 2. or 3. handfulls, and as much houſhold leven as the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of an egge, ſet the yeſt upon the fire, and then crum the leven into it, and let it boil a little while, then put in the herbs, and the roots of them, and let it be boyled thick, and lay ſome of it on a cloth every morning, and this will both draw and break and heal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Fiſtula.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a handfull of Sage, waſh it, pick and ſhred it, boil it in a pint of milk, till it be tender, then take a pennyworth of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37512:27"/>flax ſeed, beat it to powder, and when the ſage is tender thicken the milk with the flaxſeed, when it is bruiſed put thereto a pennyworth of oyle of roſes, uſe this two or three dayes twice aday.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Felon or Boyl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take half a pint of new Milk, and put ſome grated bread into it, boil them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then put thereto a handfull of ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and as much ſouthernwood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chopped fine, ſo boyl them to a pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, when it is boiled ſtir into it almoſt a ſpoonfull of caſtle ſoap ſcraped.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sirrup of Sider.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of French Barley one ſpoonfull, boil it in ſeveral waters, of madder root, aſperagus root, red dock root, each two drams thin ſliced, Ceterach epithimum, each half an ounce, polipody ſix drams, maidenhair two pugills, the tops of hops a quarter of a handfull, egremony and fumitory, each half a handfull, ſweet fennel ſeeds, anniſeeds, each one dram bruiſed, mechoacan one dram and a half,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37512:28"/>the juices of 4 handfulls of ſcurvy graſs, &amp; of two handfulls of watercreſſes infuſe all theſe in 3. pints of <hi>ſider</hi> (made of pippins &amp; pearmains) one night, in the morning boil them over a gentle fire, untill a pint or thereabouts of the liquor be left, ſtrain it thorow a linen ſtrainer into a baſon: Take three ounces of this decoction and infuſe into it being warm, half an ounce of the beſt Rha. thin ſliced, and two ſcruples of choſen cinnamon bruiſed 24. hours in a ſilver cup well covered, the next morning ſtrain out the liquor from the Rha. put into the reſt of the former decoction: This decoction being mixed with the infuſion and juices put into a skillet with a pound of powder ſugar and the white of an egge well beaten and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed with ſome of the liquor, this don, ſet it on a fire of hot coals, when it boils up take it from the fire, and ſtrain it through a cotten ſtrainer, then the skillet being clean waſhed again, put in your liquor and let it boil over a gentle fire unto the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37512:28"/>conſiſtence and height of a ſirrup: The doſe or quantity to take of this Sirrup may be one ounce and a half every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it will be the more effectual if you adde one ſcruple of <hi>Cremor Tartari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Burn or Scald.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take three handfulls of the green rind of elder, as much green gooſe dung, beat theſe and boil them a pretty while in a pound of freſh butter, ſtrain it out very hard, and keep it in an earthen pot, ſtir it till it be almoſt cold and when you uſe it melt thereof and anoint the ſore with a feather, and lay a primroſe leaf next the ſore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Barrows greaſe, ſengreen, chop them and bil them altogether, then ſtrain it and uſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a great red Onon, and cut a round hole therein, and fill it with black ſoap, and roaſt it in embers till it be ſoft, and apply it to the navel as hot as may be.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37512:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give the patient a good draught of fair water and wheat flower mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and burn partridge feathers before them in a chafing diſh with coals.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A pretious ointment good for all kind of Sciaticaes, dry itches, ſtrains of ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news or veins, for any ſcalding with gunpowder, ſhingles, bliſters, venoms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Organy, mints, thyme, hyſſop, ſpike leaves and flowers, wormwood, feather few, orpen, ſage, vervain, coſtma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, betony, mary golds, ſtems and flowers, of each of theſe a good handfull, and of valerian two good handfulls; take the tendereſt part of theſe leaves from the hard-ſtalks, ſtamp them very ſmall, and ſeeth them in a clean pan with two pound of barrows greaſe finely tryed, and 4. ounces of deers ſuet, ſtir it diligently the ſpace of an hour, then ſtrain it into a clear pan, let it ſtand all night, next morning let out the water underneath the ointment, taking none but the pureſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37512:29"/>of it, ſet it on the fire again, melt it, skim it clear, put thereto 4. ounces of deers ſuet, then take it of, let it ſtand all night as before, then warme it a little, then pour it out on a clean board, cleanſe the bottom of it very clean, ſo you may keep it for your uſe 7. years.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take poſſet-drink a pint and a half, boil therein Mallows, violet leaves and lettice, of each half a handfull, camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile flowers and a little anniſeeds bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; let it boil half away, ſtrain out the liquor very well, and put thereto ſirrup of roſes, and ſirrup of violets, of each two ſpoonfulls, courſe ſugar three ſpoonfulls, ſo make a Gliſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Mallows, beets, mercury, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let leaves, pellitory of the wall, and courſe wheat bran, of every one a handfull, of camomile flowers or the leaf it ſelf, half a good handfull, of fennel ſeeds bruiſed two ſpoonfulls, boil them in a quart of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37512:30"/>fair water, till more then half be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then ſtrain it well, and diſſolve therein 4. ſpoonfulls of ſallet oyle, (or for want thereof as much butter) and two ounces of courſe ſugar: but if the party be troubled with wind, you may adde thereto a ſpoonfull of bay-berries bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſheeps feet, ſodden with the wool on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take three quarters of a wine pint of Milk warme from the Cow, keep it in the ſame temper by ſetting it in a skillet of hot water till you have diſſolved therein two ounces of diacatholicon, and two ounces of red ſugar, and put it into a bag, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pint of Milk, a quart of beer, and make clear poſſet drink thereof, take off the curd, then put therein of anniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, and ſweet fennelſeeds each two ounces, boil theſe to half a pint or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more, ſtrain it out very hard, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37512:30"/>put thereto two ounces of brown ſugar candy and a little bay ſalt with two ſpoonfulls of oil of olive.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take an ale-quart of Barley water, made with cool herbs and raiſins (as you make it uſually to drink) ſet it on the fire; then flea a ſmall cock chicken (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill warme) and draw it, break all the bones, ſo put it into that water, with a handfull of endive, as much violet leaves, a ſuccory root and a parſley root, one ounce of fennel ſeeds bruiſed, boil all theſe to half a pint, then ſtrain it out hard, and beat into it the yolks of two new laid eggs, one ounce of ſugar candy, and two ſpoonfulls of oyle of ſweet almonds, and ſo apply it.</p>
               <p>All theſe <hi>Gliſters</hi> to be taken in the body neither too hot, nor yet too cold, (as milk from the cow) and unleſs in caſes of neceſſity they are to be given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4. of the clock in the afternoon, and about two hours after the patient is to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37512:31"/>drink a draught of mace ale; when it hath done working they muſt go warme and early to bed after a light ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52-100" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <hi>For aches, bruiſes, gouts, ſtiches, lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, cramps, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Sage, Rue, of each one pound, of wormwood and bayes each half a Pound, ſheeps ſuet clean picked three Pound; all theſe muſt be ſtamped toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till none of the ſuet be ſeen, but all one; then put thereto of oyle olive pure and ſweet a pottle, and work it well together, and after put it into a fine baſon, and cover it and let it ſtand eight dayes, and then take it out, being moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as it is, break it into a braſs pan, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſoft fire under it, alwayes ſtirring it till the herbs begin to become crack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hard, and then take it off, and ſet it a little while to cool, then ſtrain ir, and when it is ſtrained, put into it an ounce of oyle of ſpike, and anoint the geieſ therewith warme.</p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37512:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the falling ſickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take that part of a womans Scull that groweth on the hinder part of the head, (it is whiterthen the reſt of the ſcull) beat it very fine, and give the party (in ſirrup of violets) as much as a peaſe at a time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To draw the ague from any ſore or in the leggs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Wormwood and henbane, each a handful, ſhred them into a quart of milk, put in a handfull of red roſe leaves, and as much beaten oatmeal as will make it a pultice, a good quantity of ſwines greaſe, and when it is well boiled apply it to the ſore very hot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For an old ſore that runneth with thin ſubſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pint of running water and a pint of whitewine vinegar; boil therein a new piece of hollan, thus bath with this liquor a place a hands breath above the ſore, and lay the cloth on the ſame place, and this you muſt do morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing untill the cure be wrought.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37512:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſwelling of the knees or any other place that cometh of wind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a quantity of Sack, put therein ſome roſemary and a little pepper groſly beaten, put them all into a ſtone jugg, ſtop it cloſe, and let it boil ſoftly until half be conſumed, then bath the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with that is grieved as hot as may be, then dip a linnen rag and bind it on the place two or three times aday, keep it warme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To diſſolve any knob or hard ſwelling in the face or elſewhere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the whiteſt Frankinſence, and the white of an egge, beat them to a ſalve in a ſtone mortar, ſpread a plaiſter therewith, and ſo apply it to the place grieved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Unguentum aureum.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>A prectious oyntment for all manner of aches and bruiſes, and alſo for the gout.</head>
                  <item>1. Violet leaves and flowers.</item>
                  <item>2. Primroſe leaves and flowers.</item>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37512:32"/>
                  <item>3. Cowſlip leaves and flowers.</item>
                  <item>4. Elder leaves and flowers.</item>
                  <item>5. White Lilly flowers.</item>
                  <item>6. St. Johns Wort.</item>
                  <item>7. Rag-wort.</item>
                  <item>8. Mug-wort.</item>
                  <item>9. Sage.</item>
                  <item>10. Neppe.</item>
                  <item>11. Smalledge.</item>
                  <item>12. Margerome.</item>
                  <item>13. Lavender.</item>
                  <item>14. Southernwood.</item>
                  <item>15. Roſemary.</item>
                  <item>16. Roſe leaves blown.</item>
                  <item>17. Rue.</item>
                  <item>18. Lavender-Cotten.</item>
                  <item>19. Featherfue.</item>
                  <item>20. Tanſie.</item>
                  <item>21. Lovage.</item>
                  <item>22. Mynts.</item>
                  <item>23. Camomil.</item>
                  <item>24. Thyme.</item>
                  <item>25. Clarye.</item>
                  <item>26. Oak of Jeruſalem.</item>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37512:33"/>
                  <item>27. Penniroyal.</item>
                  <item>28. Safron of the willow.</item>
                  <item>29. Hyſſop.</item>
                  <item>30. Balme.</item>
                  <item>31. White Mynts.</item>
                  <item>32. Marygolds.</item>
                  <item>33. Piony leaves.</item>
                  <item>34. Bay leaves.</item>
                  <item>35. Dill.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Take of each of the above named herbs and beat them in a mortar, and put them in a pan, with a pottle of ſweet ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let oyle, and a quart of white wine, then ſet it over the fire, and let it boil ſoftly untill the wine be conſumed, ſtirring it all the while, then take it from the fire and let it cool, then ſtrain it through a linnen cloth and keep it in a glaſs; and when you anoint herewith, you muſt chafe it in by the fire, and apply next to the place the bladder of a hog, that the cloth drink not up the oyle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Ringworm in the neck.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take hounds dung that is white and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37512:33"/>dry, ſtamp it, put it in an earthen pot, with wine untill it be thick, ſpread a plaiſter therewith an lay it on the ſore, and let the patient bloud under the tongue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Sciatica or other ach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a quart of the oyle of Trotters, and put thereto three handfulls of neppe, two handfulls of camomil, boil them all on a ſoft fire, till it be very green, then ſtrain out the herbs, and put into it an ounce of ginger finely beaten and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and ſtir it together as it cooleth; chafe the place that is grieved againſt the fire with this ointment both morning and evening.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Scarre felſtered with bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Taka Liturgy of gold 4. ounces, oyle olive, young ſwines greaſe, each of them two ounces, green coperas a quarter of an ounce, ceruce half an ounce; ſeeth them altogether on the fire (continually ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them with an aſhen ſtick, the bark pilled off) put it being in the boiling
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37512:34"/>three ounces of white wax, when it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> boiled to a pure white, take it off ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtirring it till it be cold, then anoint you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands with oyle, and work it up by roll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wrap it in an oyled paper and keep it in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cloſe box.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A green ſalve to heal any ſore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Beares greaſe white waſhed and well drained half a pound, of the leaves and flowers of <hi>S. Iohns</hi> wort, of knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſs, of each of theſe a handfull, of aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en leaves to handfulls, beat them firſt very ſmall, and then mingling them with the greaſe beat them again, and boil them ſtirring them a good ſpace, then put in two ounces of yellow wax, and a ſpoonfull of turpentine, ſo let them boil a little, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Salve for a new wound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Elecampane, engliſh to bacco, the great orpin, Jacobs ladder, each half a handfull, beat theſe in a mortar very fine, then put to them above half a pound of barrows greaſe, beat them well together
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37512:34"/>untill the greaſe be very green, and then ſet them on a ſoft fire, a good ſpace, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing it continually: then put to them yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wax and rozen, of each one onnce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urpentine a ſpoonfull, camphire and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oes, of each a little quantity, boil them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ltogether, then take them off and ſtrain them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A medicine for the Ague to apply to the Wriſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take leaves of red Sage, as much rue, and about twenty leaves of ſtock gilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lowers; cut all theſe very ſmall upon a trencher, then take two pieces of calves deather (about 4. fingers breadth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and ſpread the ſame with venice turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and upon the turpentine ſpread the aforeſaid herbs, and upon the herbs you muſt ſcrape a nutmeg, ſo lay it to the wriſts, an hour before the fit, and when you perceive the fit to be coming, let the party eat a toſte ſopped in aquavite and pepper.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37512:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An approved mediciue for the Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Sickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take one ounce of the filings of ſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and lay it in ſoak 4. dayes in the beſt wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vinegar, then ſet it before the fire to dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and then beat it to powder and ſearce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> very ſmall, then take two ounces of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds, and beat them and ſearce the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſmall, and one ounce of fine ſugar beate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſearced, then mingle them together and put into it a ſpoonfull of fine powder of red coral, there muſt be twice a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> much of theſe anniſeeds and ſugar a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is ſteel, to be done by weight.</p>
               <p>They muſt take it in a morning faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as much as will lie upon a knive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> point at three times, and as much mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> two hours before ſupper, and uſe mode<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rate exerciſe after it till they ſweat, and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when they have done all, then take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> purge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Purging-Diet Ale for the Dropſie, Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, to open the Liver and Spleen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Dock roots, madder roots
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37512:35"/>horſe radiſh roots, ſmalledge roots, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pody of the oak, ſarſaparilla, caper &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marisk roots, of each 2. ounces; of agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, maidenhair, ceterack, tamerisk, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>curv ygraſs, brooklime, water-creſſes, green wormwood, each one good hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull, ſena ſix ounces, hermodactills and mechoachan, thabarb, agarick, each one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unce; anniſeeds, ſweet fennel ſeeds, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oots of faſſafras and licorice, each one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unce, cinamon, ginger, mace, each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alf an ounce; prepare theſe and put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem into a thin bolter bag, with two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adds of ſteel, and hang in 4. gallons of new ale, letting them work together with a pint of the juice of ſea ſcurvy graſs, and as much of water-creſſes.</p>
               <p>They are to drink morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing large draughts, ſo as to work 3. or 4. times daily, alſo morning and evening to take two or three pills of ſteel.</p>
               <p>Bleed the patient firſt at the liver right arme vein, and let out ſeven ounces of bloud, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:37512:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>To purge the Spleen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Ceterack, liverwort, miden hair, of each a handfull, polipody of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> oak ſix ounces; ſena, bark of capers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> marisk, aſh and bay each one oun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and roots of fennel, licorice and ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ledge, as much ſeeds of ſweet fenne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and nettles each two drams; boil a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe in two quarts of the juice of ſcun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> graſs and watercreſſes, till all be ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thick, keeping it clean skimmed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then ſtrain it and infuſe in it over a gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fire, of rabarb thin ſliced one ounc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ginger ſliced two ſcruples, ſafron a dram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrain it very hard, and ſet it over the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> again, and put into it half a pound o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prunes clean waſhed with a pound and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> half of ſugar, and a branch of roſema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> being ſtewed; take 4. or 5. ſpoonfull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and 3. or 4. prunes in the morning, and at going to bed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agreen ſalve for any kind of ach, ſore ſtrain, bruiſe or wound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two pound of Mutton and Bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37512:36"/>ſuet tryed together, and two pound of yellow roſen, two pints of neats-foot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyle, and as much verdigreaſe bruiſed as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>will cover it, and put them altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a braſs kettle, and ſet them over a cleer fire to boil a good pretty while, and ſtir it till it be well melted, and turn green, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut the cleareſt of it out into a pipkin, and ſo it will keep a year or two; if you will have it to draw a ſore, you muſt put a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more rozen into it, if it be to anoint any part that is bruiſed or ſtreined, or any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, then you muſt chafe it in with your hand, againſt the fire, and lay a warm cloth upon it, <hi>&amp;c. Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The yellow Salve good for any Sore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Turpentine and Rozen each two ounces, and bruiſe them very ſmall, and put them into an earthen red pipkin, of bees wax one ounce, cut it very ſmall, of neats-foot oyle two ounces, ſet them all on hot embers, ſtir them ſo, as they may incorporate, skim it very clean, and take heed they boil not.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:37512:37"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Drink for the Rickets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a handfull of the bark of Ivy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> much of the bark of aſh, a good handf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of tamarisk, put it into two gallons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> beer, and when it is a fortnight old, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the child drink it with meat, and at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> times for ſix weeks or two months ſprin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and fall.</p>
               <p>To this quantity of drink ſlice a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ounce of Rhabard, and put it in with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bark.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Direction for the Plague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take three pints of malmſey (or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Muſcadell) and boil therein ſage and ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> each a handfull, till a pint be waſted, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrain it and ſet it over the fire again, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> put to it three penniworth of long pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and half an ounce of ginger, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quarter of an ounce of nutmegs, all be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en together, ſo let it boil a little altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then put therein 4. penniworth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mithridate, two penniworth of treacl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and a quarter of a pint of the beſt ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lica water.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37512:37"/>
               <p>Keep this carefully, and take of it morning and evening, a ſpoonfull or two if you be already infected, and ſwear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, if not, then take once aday one ſpoonfull, half in the morning and half in the evening all the plague time: this is (if God pleaſe) ſufficient, for there was never man, woman or child, that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. It is not only good for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Plague called the Stiches, but for the ſmall Pox, Meaſles, Surfets, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Snail Water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a peck of garden Snails, and waſh them in a great bowl of beer. Then make your chimney very clean, and pour out half a buſhel of charcole on the fire, &amp; when they are kindled throughly, then with a ſhovel make a hole and pour in the Snails, ſcutter ſome of the fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and ſo let them roſte as long as you hear them make a noiſe, then take them out, and with a kniſe and a courſe cloth, pick them and wipe all the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37512:38"/>green froth from them very clean, then put them into a ſtone mortar and bruiſe them ſhells and all, take alſo a quart o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> earth wormes, ſlice them and ſcour them with ſalt, then waſh them and bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them to pieces in a ſtone mortar, then (the pot being made very clean, upon which you ſet your Limbeck) put them into it, and about two handfulls of ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica laid in the bottom, and two handfulls of ſelendine upon that, then put in a quart of roſemary flowers, and alſo put in of roſemary flowers, and alſo put in of egrimony bearsfoot, dock roots, of the bark of barbara tree, woodſorrel and betony, of each two handfulls, rue half a handfull, fenegreek &amp; turmerick, each an ounce, ſaffron well dryed and beaten to powder the weight of ſix pence, then pour in three gallons of the ſtrongeſt ale you can get, great meaſure and cover your pot, and let it ſtand ſo all night in the place where you mean to put fire un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it in the morning, then put to them three ounces of cloves beaten to powder
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37512:38"/>before you put fire to it, and put thereto ſix ounces of harts-horn grated or filed to powder before you weigh it, you muſt not ſtir it after the harts horn is put into it, leaſt it go down to the bottom, then ſet on the limbeck, and receive your wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in pints, or it may be diſtilled in bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo, the firſt water is the ſtrongeſt, and it muſt be received by it ſelf, the laſt is the ſmalleſt, and may be amended by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in of the ſtrongeſt when it is uſed.</p>
               <p>The water muſt be given to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient in the morning, who muſt faſt two hours after it, and not ſleep but uſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate exerciſe upon it, or it may be given bet wixt meals two hours before each meal, he muſt take two ſpoonfuls of the ſtrongeſt with 4. ſpoonfulls of ale or white wine, and when you give the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſort, you may give as much water as drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Purge yet comfortable both for the Spleen and Liver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a knuckle of Veal and cut away
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37512:39"/>all the fleſh and fat, then break all the bones and waſh them very clean, put it into a pipkin to a gallon of water, ſet it a ſeething, ſcum it ſo long as any thing will ariſe, then put to it a quarter of a pound of raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, and half as many currans, two fennel roots, three parſley roots, one ſuccory root, half a handfull of burrage, as much ſuccory and endive, a like quantity of violet leaves and ſtraw berry leaves, half a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of liverwort, as much ſcabius, let all theſe boil together till half of the broth be conſumed, then take it off the fire, put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it half an ounce of the beſt ſena a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ounce, of epithimum half an ounce of tamarisk, then ſet it on hot embers and let it infuſe three hours, then take it and ſtrain it into a baſon, and take it for your uſe; this will ſerve 4. dayes to take warm at ſeven of the clock in the morning, and at 4. in the afternoon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For any pain in the Ears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a quart of new Milk, and put
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37512:39"/>therein a good quantity of cloves bruiſed as will make it ſtrong, then ſet it on the fire in a clean skillet, and let it boil till it hath taken all the ſtrength out of the cloves, then take it boiling hot off the fire, and put it into a narrow mouthed pot, and hold it to the Ear of the party that the ſume may go into the head, and if it be cold heat it again, uſe this for an hour together or more, as you ſhall find cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Te heal a Fiſtula, or any old Canker or Sore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a gallon of Smiths water ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through a cloth, then take half a grain of white coperas, and 4. penniworth of camphire, boil them together till the third part of the water be conſumed, cleanſe it into a bottle or glaſs, if it be a fiſtula, cleanſe it with a ſquirt and ſo waſh it to the bottom, dip a cloth in the water being warmed and lay upon it, roul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove and beneath the place that it go no further, if it be not an open ſore or a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37512:40"/>only, waſh it and dip a cloth and lay it on warm, and dreſs it thrice aday, and by Gods grace it will heal it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A General Cordial for the Catharh and Conſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The particulars are theſe; Avens, mouſear, verven, S. Johns wort, red ſage, plantain, hyſſop, herb John, violet leaves, betony in the wood, roſemary, ſmalledge ſeed an ounce, two ounces of elecam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pane roots ſliced thin, worm wood, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rygold and the leaves, balm of the fineſt, ſpearmint.</p>
               <p>Take of each of theſe herbs a pound weight, and infuſe them in nine gallons of ſtrong ale, a day and a night, then draw it through a limbeck, and you ſhall have an excellent water, which when you purpoſe to drink of it put in ſome ſugar.</p>
               <p>It is good generally for any diſeaſe of the head and body and much ſtrengthening the ſtomach, drink it at all times as you
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37512:40"/>will drink ſtrong water, and God bleſs it to you, Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Swelling in the Knees.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Rue and Burrage, and ſtamp them together with hony, and ſo apply it to the Knees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A purging Diet-drink, good againſt the Scurvy, Dropſie, and alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore and ſtrengthen the body, to be uſed ſpring and fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Saſſafras, lignum rhodium and mace, each half an ounce, china roots one ounce, licorice ſix ounces, anniſeeds 4. ounces, Roman wormwood, ſage, roſemary, betony, balm, mugwort, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentil roots, Lady mantle, egrimony clotsfoot, ſanacle, mouſeare, ſcabius, herb Robert, ragwort, marſh mallow roots, and columbine roots, of each of theſe one handfull; cut and bruiſe the wood and roots, break or cut the herbs; boil all in ſix gallons of ſtrong ale-wort, till two gallons be conſumed, then put the woods and herbs into ſix gallons
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37512:41"/>more of ſecond wort, boil that likewiſe with a few hops, and ſtrain it out, and put in an ounce of rhabarb, and three ounces of ſena, ſo ſet it on working and tun it up with a rha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſena bag, drink thereof once, twice, or thrice in a day as ye find cauſe, after ten dayes ſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For an Impoſtume in the head, Dropſie, Feaver, and all manner of aches and Impoſtumes in the head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Spikenard two penniworth, grind it, and boil it with vinegar, when it is boiled and cold, put to it honey and muſtard a ſawcer full, mingle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, uſe a ſpoonfull at once, hold it in your mouth two Creeds, then let it out into a baſon, uſe this when you go to bed, three dayes together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pro Gonorkaea, ad purgand. Renas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Rec. Caſſia fiſtula extract. ſirrup de Nymphea two ounces, rhab. pul. two drams, fiat electuar. recept. mane in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. cum vino albo, 4. dies.</p>
               <p>Poſt rec. A quaroſar. rub. one pound,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37512:41"/>album de ovo recent. ſaccharum album &amp; muſcat. 9. s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For old wounds, Vlcers, Cancers, Scabs, Itch or Fiſtula's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Virginia Tobacco ſtalks one pound, ſpring water one gallon, boil it to three pints, put it into a bottle, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger you keep it the better, the way to uſe it is to wet a linnen cloth in the water a little warmed, and ſo bath well the wound or place, do ſo morning and evening.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the M grim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Betony, vervain, camomile, featherfue, wormwood, roſemary, each alike, put them into a bag, and ſeeth them in white wine, and lay them to the head as hot as you can ſuffer it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Oyntment for Reumatick Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take hogs lard well tryed 3. ounces. ſet to ſteep in red roſewater ſix hours, then waſh it twelve times in whitewine wherein lapis Tutia and lapis Calumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris hath been quenched, then adde the Caluminaris and Tutia being beat red
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37512:42"/>hot and quench'd in whitewine (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſix times, each an ounce, lapis he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matitis two ſcruples, aloes twelve grains, ſeed pearl prepared ſix grains, mix it very well together and adde a little fennel wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as much as ſhall be neceſſary to make it liquid enough.</p>
               <p>Anoint the eye lids herewith, it will take away ſpots or any thing that grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about the eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Quinzy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take album Grecum pul. a handfull of rue beat ſmall, boil them in ſweet ſallet oyle till they become thick, then ſpread it on a cloth, plaiſter-wiſe, and apply it to the ſore from ear to ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Againſt the trembling of the Heart, and Convulſion fits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take powder of Gold 1. penniworth, ſix penny weight of Amber, ſix penny weight of pearl, ſix penny weight of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, bezoar five grains, half an ounce of piony root, twelve penny weight of a ſcull of an anatomy, pul. take as much as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37512:42"/>will lie upon a ſix pence in a ſpoonfull of endive water every morning, and drink a good draught after it.</p>
               <p>Take Caſſia one ounce, Rha. pul. ten grains, ſirrup. violar. recept in poſſeto cum vino albo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To boil Turpentine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt waſh it, then boil it in plantain or roſe water till it come to the conſiſtence of wax, then take it out and reſerve it, make pills; take 3. or 4. when you go to bed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For miſcarrying, and to ſtop the Reds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Claret wine a quart, mouſear, ſhepherds purſe, each a handfull, boil it altogether with a ſtick of cinamon, and ſweeten it with ſugar, and drink a draught of it often warme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To ſtay vomiting bloud, by reaſon of an inward bruiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Quench Steel in Milk and drink it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; or take ſperma-ceti in any warm drink, once or twice.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:37512:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Vomit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take roch Allom one ounce pul. and put it into half a pint of ſmall beer, let it ſtand warm all night, and in the morning ſtrain it, and let the patient drink it off, this fetcheth flegme off the ſtomach.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take five grains of Stibium in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in 4. or 5. ſpoonfulls of whitewine, and let it ſtand all night, and in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning take the wine clean from the ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium, and drink it faſting, and when it hath once wrought, take poſſet drink between every vomit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To break a Boyle or Felon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a great Onion, cut the top, and take ſo much out of it as you may fill it up with half a ſpoonfull of Jeans treacle, and cover it with the piece again, bind it with a thred, and roſt it in the embers in a brown paper, and when it's roſted, break it and mingle it together, and lay ſome of it to the Boyl which you would have broken.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:37512:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Child with a broken Belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Polipody of the wall, Juniper berryes, comphrey roots, the skin of the yolk of an egg, dry all theſe and beat them together, then put them in a pint of good ale, and give it every day warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the falling ſickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Gold, pearl, coral, and bezoar, and amber, each 4. ſcruples, piony ſeeds as much, and ſingle piony roots alike quantity, pul. omnes, and take as much of the powder as will lie on a groat, in a ſpoonfull of white endive water every morning faſting, untill a quarter of the water be in ſuch manner ſpent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Collick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Figgs good ſtore, and new mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard made with vinegar, ſtamp them well together, and put them into a linen bag, and as hot as you can ſuffer it lay it on, and hold it to the navel and belly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For bleeding at Noſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Hemp or hempen halter, and hold about your neck.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:37512:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A water to take away Wheals, Puſhes, Kernels, Swellings, Bunches, and Warts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of Bayes two pound, white Frankinſence, Maſtich, gum arabick and turpentine, each three ounces, beat thoſe things which may be beaten, then min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them altogether, diſtill them in a lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, and after put into the water half a pound of the aſhes of earth burned, and then diſtill it again, and keep it as a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to beſtow on your beſt friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Water for the Head-ach, and to cauſe reſt in weakneſs or Child-bed Women.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Primroſe leaves and wood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, each one handfull, ſteep them twelve hours in as much new milk as will cover them, then diſtill them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; then in Cowſlip time, ſteep in this water two good handfulls of cowſlip flowers, and one good handfull of unſet hyſſop, ſo let it ſtand 4. hours, then ſtill it altogether, and give ſix or eight ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37512:44"/>at a time warme with a little ſugar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An oyntment to aſſwage a ſwelled ſore Breaſt, or any other ſwelling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Egrimony and boil it in butter or hoggs lard to an ointment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with anoint the ſwelled Breaſt; alſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimony boiled in milk and thicked up with bread, and put a little honey into it, and laid to the Breaſt, aſſwages a hard ſwelled breaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For bleeding Gumms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the thin ſhaving of the inſide of a piece of Spaniſh leather and hold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Gumms ſtayes it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the dead Palſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take 4. penniweight of the Horn that groweth in the inſide of a horſes Knee, dryed and beat to powder, give it with two ſpoonfulls of the juice of the green leaves of blew periwinkles in a fit, and let them drink a draught of hot ſack after it, do this every other day for three dayes, and tie the ſtring of this perewinkle on the dead member, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37512:45"/>ſhift it every other day; theſe ſtrings cure the cramp, being tyed on the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Gout, Stiches, and to open obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, moſt excellent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take half a pound of red Saunders, and ſteep it in a pint and a half of white wine, let it ſteep all night, the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrain it and drink it, do this two or three dayes together, then forbear it as long, after take it again, in half a ſcore times taking it hath cured thoſe of the Gout, which for three years together have not been able to go; it doth work upwards and downwards 3. or 4. times, and will for a little time make them ſick, but is moſt harmleſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Pluriſce of wind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Horſe dung, camomile and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſley fryed with butter and vinegar, and apply it as hot as may be ſuffered divers times; or wet rye meal with the ſick par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties water, and make a cake of it, ſlit the cake in the middle, and ſpread with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37512:45"/>London treacle, and apply it to the ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Wind, Mother, or Convulſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Coral, Amber and Jeat, each alike weight, beat them into fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, take the quantity of an hazel nut, and put it into a ſpoon with ſome caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or broth, take two or three ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls, eat not in two or three hours after.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A ſover agin water for old Vlcers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two penniworth of pure white coperas, put it into a pint of cleer ſpring water, ſet it on a ſoft fire, that it may only ſimmer, take off the ſcum with a feather, ſo ſoon as the coperas is diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, take it off and put it into a glaſs or ſtone bottle; the longer it is kept the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it will be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe this defenſive Plaiſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bole Armonick, the white of an egg, and white wine vinegar; to keep the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice open put into the wound gentian wood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Purge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Manna one ounce and a half,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37512:46"/>diſſolve it in clarified whay, and drink it in the morning faſting, uſe it two or three dayes as you ſee cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For heat in the Back.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take juice of Lemons and vinegar, and dip a cloth in it, and apply it to the Back oftentimes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Head-ach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of Wormwood, ſtrong vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar and roſe water, and mingle them together and boil them, and lay them as hot as you may ſuffer it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To dry up a Sore that iſſues with water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Ale or Beer, boil in it ſage till it be ſtrong, then put in a quantity of allom and honey, and bath the part ill affected, and lay of the ſage leaves that were boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on the ſore place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take about Michaelmas time, the ripeſt and rankeſt nettle ſeeds you can get, dry them in the ſun or in an oven, and ſo
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37512:46"/>keep them cloſe in a paper, and when the patient feels the Mother to riſe, take a ſpoon heaped of theſe ſeeds beat in a mortar, in white wine or beer and let them drink it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Piles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take white Starch pul. and put on the Piles; or a great onion, roſt it, ſpread it flat, and ſpread it over with mithridate, and apply it warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Rickets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſallet Oyle one pint, camomile with the flowers three handfulls, ſtrip it from the ſtalks, boil one handfull firſt in the oyle and take it up, then the ſecond, and the third, then put the camomil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two bags, and anoint the ſides ſtroak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it downward with the oyle, then lay on the bags warm, anoint it twice aday where the knots are, and lay ſpeedwell in their drink continually, then take a purge of Rha. five or ſix grains pul. in poſſet, uſe it nine dayes together, then ceaſe a fortnight, and uſe it again.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:37512:47"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Oyntment for the Rickets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Roſemary, Bay leaves, Camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, tops of lavender, alehoof, unſet hyſſop, each one handfull ſhred together and beat in a mortar, and boiled together in a pound of freſh butter an hour, then ſtrain it out, and with this anoint the child, his ſides, knees, and down to his feet, evening and morning a quarter of an hour; this muſt be made in May.</p>
               <p>Take cloves of Fox-fern root, alias oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, bruiſed and boiled in milk, take it in the morning faſting and and faſt an hour after it, or make the root into pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and give it in beer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Sirrup for the Rickets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take running water one quart, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhair, ſage of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> coltsfoor, each one ounce, licorice ſliced, anniſeeds brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed each an ounce and a half, Fox-fern root ſliced one ounce, liverwort one handfull, twenty figgs ſliced; boil all theſe to the half, then ſtrain it, put to it
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37512:47"/>fine ſugar one pound and a half, peatle prepared three ounces; boil altogether, then ſtrain it, and give the child one ſpoonfull firſt and laſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pills to ſtay vomiting and cleanſe the ſtomach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Alloes ſiccatrina, adde to it nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg grated, two or three drops of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let oyle, as much aquavite, and a little ſirrup of roſes, when 'tis diſſolved toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, put a drop of oyle upon your fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, make it into pills, whereof take two in a morning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To make the Palſie oyle to anoint twice aday for any benummedneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Neats foot oyle, roſemary tops. ſweet marjoram two handfulls, lavender tops or leaves before it ſhoot to blow, two handfulls, red ſage one handfull; chop them ſmall, and put them to the oyle, and let it boil apace till the herbs be changed, and the ointment of a fair green colour, then ſtrain it out and keep
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37512:48"/>it in a glaſs ſtopt for uſe, it will laſt ſeven years in its full force and virtue; adde to it camomile, wormwood, time and hyſlop.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Stone in the Kidneys, and them that make bloudy water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take milk and make a clear poſſet, wherein boil a handfull of plantain, a ſtick or two of licorice, a ſlice or two of comphrey root, drink them off firſt and laſt, and ſometimes drink the juice of plantain either by it ſelf or in beer.</p>
               <p>Take alſo pills of Turpentine waſht in plantain water, and made up in pills with gum arabick, and rapt up in ſugar and ſwallowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Burn or Scald.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Thorn-apple leaves, ſtamp them or cut them ſmall, and boil them in Hogges lard to any oyntment. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:37512:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Falling—ſickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a Jay, pull off the feathers, then take out the gutts, and fill it full with cominſeeds and anniſeeds, and then bake it till it is dry to beat to powder with the head on and leggs, drink this in porrage or ale.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Flos Vnguentorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Rozen, per rozen each a pound and a half, virgins wax and frankinſence each a pound and a quarter, maſtich one ounce, harts tallow or deers ſuet 4. pound, camphire two ounces; melt that which is to be melted, and pound that which is to be pounded, and ſift it fine, and boil them over the fire, and then ſtrain them through a canvas cloth into a pottle of white wine, then boil them all with the other ingredients to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then let it cool to bloud warm, then put to them a quarter of a pound of turpentine, ſtirring it till it be thorough
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37512:49"/>cold, and make it up in rolls, and keep it to your uſe, as the beſt and moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſalve that can be made.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Virtues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This medicine is good for all manner of diſeaſes that are written hereafter, <hi>viz.</hi> for old wounds, and it is moſt cleanſing and well ſoken, and gendreth fleſh and healeth more in a week, than any other in a month, and ſuffereth no corruption in a wound, nor no evill fleſh to be gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred therein, it's good for the head-ach and ſingings in the brain, for all manner of impoſtumes, for ſounding in the ears, and ſinews ſprung or cut, and draweth out a broken bone or thorn, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing that is in a wound; it is good for biting or ſtinging of a venemous beaſt, and it healeth all manner of bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches without, it is good for a feſter, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, noli me tangere, it draweth out all ach of the liver, ſpleen or reins, healeth
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37512:49"/>the emrods, and is a good cearcloth for gouts and peſtilent diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another flos Vnguentorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Rozen, per rozen each a pound and half, olibanum, dears ſuet, white wax, of each 4. ounces, maſtich and mirtle, each an ounce, venice turpentine two ounces, whitewine a pottle, your wax and ſuet being finely ſhred, muſt be firſt molten upon a ſoft fire; then put in your rozen and per rozen, and ſtir them well till they be melted, then ſtrain the ſtuff into a hot pan, then have ready your olibanum, maſtich and mirrhe, ground ſmall and finely ſearced, and let it all melt together, your white wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomthing warm, pour in by little and little, then take it from the fire, and put in your turpentine, and ſtir it, and laſt of all, your camphire being in powder, and ſtir it till it be cold, then make it up in rolls, and keep it in red leather to your uſe.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:37512:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>The manner how to cut the Plaiſters to cure theſe Diſeaſes, are</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Navel, three inches ſquare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To ſtop the Flux of the Belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Reins, ſix inches long and four inches broad.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Flux of the Reins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſtomach, four inches broad and ſix deep.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the wind or pain in the ſtomach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſhortneſs of Breath or Tiſsick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take eight or nine heads of Garlick, according to the conſtitution of the party, peel and cut off the ends of each clove, and put them into a pipkin, with a quarter of a pound of butter unſalted, boil it till the Garlick turn red, then run it through ſuch a thing as a milk ſtrainer,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37512:50"/>then put it into a pipkin again, with a quarter of a pound of butter more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalted, and the beſt honey one pound, boil it till the skim is well riſen, then take it off and skim it, and ſtrow in an ounce of the powder of Elecampane roots, then let it boil three or 4. Walms, take it off the fire, and ſtirre in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſix penniworth of Saffron, from the firſt to the laſt, you muſt ſtirre it while it is boiling, except the time while the skim of the Honey is riſing; eat the quantity of a ſmall nutmeg every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scabs in Childrens heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take freſh Butter, and boil in it Sute of a chimney (where there is no ſeacole burned) till it be black, and therewith anoint the head, 'twill heal it though there be holes that you may turn your finger in the head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a ſwelling or bruiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take elder ſtampt and fryed with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37512:51"/>chamber lye and freſh butter, and laid all over, taketh away the ſwelling or bruiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Lungs and Gonorhea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Craw fiſhes boiled in milk, and eaten, and the milk drank firſt and laſt and in the afternoon, ſweetned with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a perilous Cough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Sage, Rue, Comin and powder of pepper, and ſeeth them in honey, and make of them an Electuary, and uſe then alſo a ſpoonfull evening and morning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stinging of an Adder or Snake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take and drink the diſtilled water of dragons, or if you have none thereof the juice, alſo ſtamp dragons and lay to the place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To procure eaſie delivery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Hyſſop, Vervain and Betony, each one handfull, ſtamp them very ſmall, and ſtrain them in good ſtale Ale, and let the patient drink a good draught
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37512:51"/>and it will help her preſently without danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To heal a Scald or Burn</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Barley meal with the juice of red fennel, make a Plaiſter thereof, and lay it on the ſore, and it will draw out the corruption and heal it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To ſtay a Flux of Bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Willow leaves and bark, boil it in wine, and drink it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the noiſe in the ears, or Tongue ſwelled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Boil Figgs in water, and let the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient drink thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To purge the Head with Sena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Sena pul. one ounce, ginger one ounce, twelve Cloves, fennel ſeeds two ounces, cinnamon and tartar, each an ounce and a half pul. omnes; take there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in white wine, a dram after ſupper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Itch, Scabs and the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take and decoct Fumitory in Ale a quart, then infuſe in it ſena an ounce and a half, raiſins of the ſun ſtoned, anniſeeds
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:37512:52"/>bruiſed, and a little ginger, drink it with ſirrup of roſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Balſome for wounds, ſwellings, veno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous bitings, and apoſtamations, old ſores and fretting ulcers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of Olive a quart, S. Johns wort, betony, centory and ſelf-heal, each 2. handfulls, ſtamp them, &amp; mingle them well, and ſo let it ſtill in a glaſs all ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and ſtrain the oyle from the herbs and ſo uſe it; adde to it tobacco flowers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To heal watering Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take red Roſe water two ounces, and put it into a bowl-glaſs, then take male frankinſence, put it on the point of a knife into a candle of virgins wax untill it begin to melt, then ſtill dip it in the water at leaſt a hundred times, untill it turn thick like balme, diſtrain it through a ſine linen cloth, &amp; anoint your eyes therewith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To expell Rheume in the face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the white of an Egge beat to an
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37512:52"/>oyle and skimmed, then temper it with the wool of a Coneys skin to a plaiſter, warm it on coals and apply it to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and the grieved place and bind it on faſt with a cloth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Collick or griping in the belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſeed of Carduus benedictus ſtamped, and drunk in poſſet ale, or any other drink doth help the grief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paſsion of the Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take juice of Bugloſs two ounces, cleanſe and purifie it at the fire, mix it with white ſugar candy two ounces, and let the patient drink it every night going to bed ten nights together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To purge Choler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſirrup Violarum cum agaric. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in Barley water, or broth of a hen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Apurge for the Kings evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Lignum Vitae 4. ounces, infuſe it on embers in 4. quarts of ſpring water 24. hours, then adde to it Polipodian 4. ounces, ſena two ounces, anniſeeds
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:37512:53"/>and ſweet fennel ſeeds, each an ounce and a half, burrage, bugloſs and For gloves, each one handfull, boil it away to the half; then give 4. or 5. ſpoonful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to a child every morning, for eight daie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together ſweetned with ſugar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Dropſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Broom, Betony, Balme, each three handfulls, put it into three gallons of ale-wort, when it is ready to be ſtopt up, let it ſtand a week, and then drink it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly a week together, or a fortnight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Medicine for the Dropſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take horſe Radiſh roots ſliced long wayes thin two ounces, ſweet fennel ſeeds bruiſed two ounces, ſmalledge and fennel roots ſliced each an ounce, the tops of time, winter ſavory, ſweet mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, water creſſes, nettles, each one handfull; boil theſe in three pints of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and three pints of wine, a quart of canary and a pint of muſcadine, cloſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37512:53"/>covered till half be conſumed, ſo remove it from the fire, and let it ſettle 3. hours, then ſtrain it, and into every draught put in one ounce of ſirrup of the five roots, it muſt be taken thrice aday, in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and at three in the afternoon, and faſt an hour after it, if the patient have the ſcurvy alſo, adde to the draughts two ſpoonfulls of the juice of ſcurvy graſs, when the patient is ready to drink it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Oyntment for the Dropſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take wal wort and Elder leaves, ſweet marjoram and water creſſes, penniroyal, each one handfull cut and bruiſed, and ſet them to ſeeth in a quart of ſweet ſallet oyle half an hour, then let them ſtand in the veſſel three dayes, then again heat them, and ſtrain it hard out, and put in as many more of the ſaid herbs, and ſeeth them as before and ſtrain it, do ſo the third time, and keep them as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent oyntment, let the ſwollen body be anointed herewith once in three
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37512:54"/>dayes, and that in the morning by a goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fire, ſtroaking it downwards an ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a ſore Breaſt in great anguiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take dung of Geeſe, the neweſt you can get, and a little leaven and a little time, ſtamp them together, and lay the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the Breaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Bruiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take red Nettles, and a quantity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bay ſalt, bruiſe them together, and la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them to the ſore or bruiſe, this is to la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to incontinently after one is bruiſed, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> often changing it will take away the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and heal the bruiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To ſtay bleeding at Noſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the bone of a Carps head, kee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it till it be dry, then beat it to powder and take a little of the bloud of the party and beat it to powder, then mingle it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and put it in a little ale or beer an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let them drink it one or twice,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the party drink wine Vinegar pint.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:37512:54"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a cold Stomach and hot Liver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take half a pint of white wine, as much Fumitory water, let them have one walme together, and ſweeten it with ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>up of violets, take of it as you ſee cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Falling ſickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Piony roots in ale pul. drink it morning and evening, take the jay pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in portage, and drink ale before it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Oyntment for the ſpleen or a ſprain, or for wind, or ſtitch in the ſide, and good for a bruiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An old Judge going from his horſe back, broke a vein, and ſpit bloud and piſt bloud, and this oyntment cured him by anointing him.</p>
               <p>Take S. John's wort two handfulls, ſweet marjoram, ſweet baſil, mints or ſperemints, of the flowers of lavender, ſpike and red roſe leaves, of each one handfull, maudlin and wild time, each half an handfull, compound them well
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:37512:55"/>together in a ſtone mortar, then put into them a pint of the beſt ſallet oyle in a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel cloſe ſtopt, and ſet it in a place where it may have moderate heat 14 dayes then ſtrain it, and put into it half a pint of malmſey, nutmegs half an ounce, large mace an ounce and a half, and pretty quantity of cinnamon, boil a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe together till the liquor be nigh hall ſpent, and ſtrain it out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100-149" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <hi>For pain in the Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chew mace in your mouth and hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it that the fume may aſcend, and ſmell to ſpikenard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Vervain, vinegar and honey mingle them well together and drink <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> oftentimes faſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Megrim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeth a little quantity of Aloes and maſtick in whitewine, and drink thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Againſt Drunkenneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take before you drink twelve ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:37512:55"/>of Betony water, and after drink as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch as you will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the falling ſickneſs and Lethargy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of Caſtor to anoint the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a worm in the ſtomach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Neppe; ſtamp it and mingle it with white wine, and give it the patient when he is grieved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſcalding, burning, itch, ſcabs, ſcald head, or any heat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Butter unwaſht, melt it ſcalding not, then pour it into fair ſpring water, and with a ſpoon labour it and waſh it untill the butter grow cold, then gather the butter together, and pour out that water, and put freſh water to the butter, till you find your butter very white, then work your water out of the butter, then work in the powder of brimſtone finely beaten, untill your butter be ſtiff and looks yellow with it, then take camphire and the feed of pompeons clean picked and husked, grind the camphire and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:37512:56"/>them together, and work it to the butter, if you will skin any burn or ſeald with it, adde to it the powder of a rotten poſt, elſe not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Piles approved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a little piece of Scarlet and burn it, and beat it to powder and ſearce it, and put to it a little honey, and anoint the part with a little piece of ſcarlet, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take horehound and hagtaper in powder faſting 4. or 5. morning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Chin Cough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the burre of an Eglantine tree and dry it to powder, and drink it in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leaden Plaiſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take two pound and 4. ounces of oyle of olive the beſt, good red lead one pound, white lead one ponnd, beaten into duſt, ſpaniſh ſoap three ounces, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate them in an earthen pot, and when the ſoap cometh upward put it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſmall fire of coals, continuing it an
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37512:56"/>hour and a half, ſtirring it with an iron ſtick, then drop of it upon a trencher, if it cleave not it is enough, ſpread it on clothes, or lay it on a board till it cools, then roll it up, it will laſt twenty years, the older the better.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Virtue of this Plaiſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame laid on the ſtomach pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes appetite, and takes away any grief in the ſtomach, its a preſent remedy for the Collick, being laid on the belly, and upon the back, it's good for the bloudy Flux, Gonorr. and all weakneſs in the back, for women with child to wear all the time they are with child, if they find any weakneſs; it healeth all ſwellings, bruiſings and aches, it breaks felons, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, and other impoſtumes, and healeth the ſame; draweth out any rotten hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, not breaking the skin, and applyed to the fundament healeth any diſeaſe there growing; the ſame laid on the head is good for the Evelo, head-ach,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37512:57"/>and the eyes, eaſeth corns, the gout, and for a ſtrain, <hi>Probatum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a bruiſe on the Stones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Mud of a Grind-ſtone and oyle of roſes tempered together and ſpread on a cloth, and apply it to the place grieved, vinegar and water boiled together and wet clothes dipt in it, and laid above a ſore ſtayes the humour, and makes it heal the better.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Dropſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Hyſſop, Time, water creſſes and calamint, each two handfulls, fennel one handfull, Radiſh roots 4. or 5. taken out of the ground freſh, ſlice them thin, licorice, anniſeeds and comminſeeds, each two ounces, boil all theſe together in a pan or pot with the quantity of three galions of fair running water, till a third part be conſumed, then put in a pottle of ſack, ſtrain it all through a linnen cloth, then put it into a ſtone or glaſs bottle cloſe ſtopt, drink of it every morning, and at 4. of the clock in the afternoon,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:37512:57"/>and as you find good of it, continueit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cool the Liver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Barley water, caſt away the firſt, and in the ſecond boil Cinquefoil, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, ſtrawberry leaves, burrage, ſorrel, egrimony, each one handfull, boil it from a pottle to three pints and ſomething more, ſtrain it, and adde to it ſirrup vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. two ſpoonfulls, roſe water 1. ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, drink it morning and evening, it cools the liver, and make the body ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the diſplacing the Mother or Whites with a Serringe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Cinnamon bruiſed one ounce, pomgranet flowers three ounces red roſe water a quarter of an ounce, boil theſe in a pint and a half of red roſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, till half be conſumed, then adde red wine half a pint, and ſtrain it for your uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Receipt of Pills.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take white Amber, Maſtick, each one ounce, aloes the beſt two ounces and a
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:37512:58"/>half, agaric two ſcruples, ariſtolochia the round and true one ſcruple, make them all in fine powder, and with a little juice of betony or ſirrup, make them in pills, make five of a dram, and take two, three or five, going to bed.</p>
               <p>They preſerve the ſtomach from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hurt, and ſuffer no ill humours to putrifie in it, for they cleanſe, mundifie and ſtrengthen the heart, ſtomach and head, makes the party cheerfull, they purge the Reins and Matrix, and helps the eyes, they are ſafe without any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a ſore Throat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Plantain, boil it in running wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a pultis, and clap it to with a cloth; this cured one that could hardly ſpeak, ſcarce ſwallow, and made him bring pieces of ſtinking fleſh out of his throat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An oyntment for a joint Ague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Colewort leaves chopt and boiled in butter to an oyntment, ſtrain it and anoint the place ill, or boil ale to an
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37512:58"/>and anoint the place with it, the ſame is good for chilblanes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To skin Nipples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Bay leaves laid on the Nipples skins them; unguentum album skins the Nipples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take pure fine Sugar and burnt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and plantain water, and a little red roſe water; boil altogether to a ſirrup, dip fine rags in it, and lay about the Nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples till it be whole, likewiſe butter and wax, and lay it on the Nipples, being melted together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnguentum album.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Hoggs Lard and waſh it in plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain water, or red roſe water, and mingle them together with white Cerus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gargle for the throat for flegme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Muſtard a ſpoonfull, three or 4. ſpoonfulls of white wine, mingle them together, uſe it every morning for flegm; likewiſe vinegar and water, is good for
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37512:59"/>the ſame; but if it be for the palſey, take muſtard and white wine vinegar, and honey, and gargle at night going to bed warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Morphew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Pippins and Elder berries baked together, or you may ſtill it and drink the water, becauſe you cannot have the berries at all times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fainting fits in Lying Inne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Boil Harts horn and Saffron in ale or beer, and put a little ſugar to it, adde to it a little winter ſavory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Cramp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Hoggs dung boiled in ſallet oyle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To purge the Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take pill Cochie a dram to an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take pill Maſtichine, a pill or two for a Child.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Electuaries purging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take for Choller elect. de Succo ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar for Flegme dia Phenicon, for Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy confect Hamec.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:37512:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Palſie and to ſtay Rheum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a quart of Ale, boil it in lavender, and put to it a little butter and ſugar, this drink morning and evening.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the yellow Jaundies moſt excellent in great extremity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Engliſh Saffron two penniworth in powder, two penniworth of tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick in powder, and two penniworth of mace in powder, mingle it with as much fine ſugar as you like to your taſte, eat e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very morning and evening as much in the pap of an apple as three nuts; if you take a purge of rhabarb after it is good, or uſe rhab. in powder with the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For one that piſſes bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyle of ſweet Almonds, new drawn, and put a little fine ſugar into it, or white ſugar candy, and take it of it firſt and laſt.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe turpentine waſht in plantain water, and made up in pills with a little roſe leaves, and a little coral.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:37512:60"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Drink for the Plague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give the party (finding himſelf ſick) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſleep ſix ſpoonfulls of Aquavitae, and therein a ſpoonfull of beaten Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, and ſo let him ſweat upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cure a Plague ſore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This belongs to Chirurgical operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and care muſt be taken at firſt to avoid repercuſſives, and apply attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive medicines.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Plaiſter to ripen a Plague ſore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take twelve fat Figgs, well beaten, one ounce, Nitre five drams, pulp of raiſins 4. drams, honey two dreams, wheat meal one dram, treacle 4. ſcruples, with a ſufficient quantity of oyle of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, work it into an emplaiſter, and apply it to the peſtilential bubo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another pultis or cataplaſme which doth draw and ripen tumours and buboes in the groin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Mallows herb and root, ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bious,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:37512:60"/>ſouthernwood, rue, each one handfull, roots of marſh mallows one ounce, freſh gathered white lilly roots, and onions peeled, each three ounces; boil them in milk to a convenient thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſtrain it, and adde to the colature, bean and wheat meal macerated in vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar each one ounce, linſeed and fene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek, each half an ounce, orris three drams, figgs and raiſins bruiſed, each one ounce and half, pigeons dung one ounce, leaven ſix drams, the yolks of two eggs; barrow hogs lard, gum ammoniacum diſſolved in vinegar 15. drams, oyle of ſcorpions one ounce, treacle a dram and an half; mix and boil them all together into a pultis, and apply it warm to the ſore at it's firſt appearing, and renew it every ſix hours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To break the ſore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſalt Butter, half an ounce, white muſtard ſeed two drams, garlick 1. dram, a little oyle of camomile; make hereof
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:37512:61"/>a pultis and apply it warm, ſpread it upon a cabbage leaf, and let it lie on 4. or 5. hours, and then if the matter be ſoft and the skin not broken, open it with a lancet or potential cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cry of <hi>Cantharides.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Tumour is opened, it muſt be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently cleauſed, for which oſe a decoction of Ariſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia the round, Agrimony, ſelf-heal, parſley roots and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tian, which boil in equal parts of wine and water, and adde a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it a little honey, which cleanſe away the poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous matter.</p>
               <p>Then uſe Tents to the Ulcer with proper unguents, and lay on it a defenſive plaulet; and after the ſore is cleanſed and the putrefaction drown away uſe a conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidating plaiſter, for which purpoſe this is proper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Conſolidative plaiſter for a Plague ſore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take dryed leaves of Ariſtolochia the round one once, maſtich, frankinſence, myrrhe, each two drams, aloes, ſiccatrin one dram, lytharg. 4. ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, red lead one ſcruples, meal of lupines one dram; powder them very fine, then diſſolve deers ſuet one ounce, hoggs greaſe half an ounce, oyle of S. John's wort ſix drams, turpentine waſhed half an ounce, wax three ounces, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate them over a gentle fire to the conſiſtence of a plaiſter, which renew twice a day.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:37512:61"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An approved Cearcloth for Aches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recip.</hi> Burgandy pitch a pound, white Virgins wax a quarter of a pound, white Frankinſenſe two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, let the Frankinſenſe be beaten and ſearced very ſmall, then take the wax and the pitch and melt them in two ſeveral pipkins, and when they are melted pour the wax into the pitch, then ſtrow in the frankinſenſe, ſtir them well together, pour all out into a baſon of fair water, and work it up into rowls, with your hands an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with butter for ſticking.</p>
               <p>Experienced ſecrets, particularly appropriated to Wowen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſtopping of the Terms, with pains in the back, belly, and other Symptoms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the beſt Rubarb three drams, of anniſeeds two pugils (a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil is as much as you can take up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your forefingers and thumb) water of mugwort and penny royal,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:37512:62"/>each three ounces, infuſe the rubarb and ſeeds in the water, and let it boil gently, then ſtrain it through a lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloath, and to it add two ounces of ſolutive ſirrup of roſes, and one ſpoonful of cinamon water, and take it in the morning faſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To make a Womans privity ſtraight and narrow as a Maid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In honeſt vvomen this is not to be diſcommended, for too much am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude and laxity of this part, is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes the cauſe of barrenneſs, and ſometimes of falling out of the womb, and renders them ingrateful to their husbands.</p>
               <p>It may be amended by purging af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the birth, and vvith fomentations, baths, liniments, and aſtringent peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes; as a fomentation with Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom vvater, and the decoction of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringent plants.</p>
               <p>Take comphrey roots, bole armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niac, <hi>ſanguis Draconis,</hi> balauſtes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:37512:62"/>maſtick each half an ounce, powder them, and make thereof a peſſary with cotton, and annoint it vvith oyl, and put it up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A fomentation for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oaken leaves, plantaine, each half a handful, comphrey roots, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome each one ounce, pomgranate pills, balauſtins, ſumach, each half an ounce, boil them in water, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the part with the decoction.</p>
               <p>A wench that made a trade of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſelling her Maiden head, uſed this decoction for a bath, which ſo cloſed up her <hi>pudenda,</hi> that ſhe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for an untouched Virgin, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of puſtule's, tumors, and ſcabs about womens privy members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though this be moſt common to thoſe that are infected vvith the <hi>French</hi> Pox, yet others may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with it proceeding from aduſt, malignant and ſharp humours.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:37512:63"/>
               <p>If it come from the Pox, take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the poyſonous cauſe of the Pox, or elſe all your labour will be in vain to goe about to cure it.</p>
               <p>But come it how it vvill, it is a troubleſome and filthy malady, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious, laſting, and hardly cured but vvith care and difficulty; and what man ſoever accompanies ſuch a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhall be infected therewith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cure puſhes and ſcabs about wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens privy places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt prepare the humors vvith convenient medicaments, as borage, ſuchory, endive, fumotery, and ſuch like: Thence proceed to purging with ſena, ſirrup of apples, of violets, of roſes ſolutive.</p>
               <p>Take Diacatholicon, and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio. hamech. Alſo uſe pills de fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria.</p>
               <p>But if you find it proceeds from the Pox, or exceſſive Venery, uſe the decoction of <hi>guiacum</hi> and <hi>ſarſa pilla,</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:37512:63"/>making proper additions, and uſe oyntments proper for ſcabs and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineſs. Or,</p>
               <p>Take three ounces of freſh hogs greaſe, and two ounces of Juice of ſumetiry, half an ounce of quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiver well kill'd, ceruſe, litharge, of each one dram, incorporate them well in a leaden morter, till they be vvell mixed into an unguent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Hemerods about the mouth of the womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the poplar Oyntment, oyl of roſes, ſweet almonds and new but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of each half an ounce, ſaffron a ſcruple, and the yolk of an egg, mix them for an ointment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take muſcilage of quince ſeeds, and marſh-mallows, each half an ounce, oyl of roſes, hens greaſe, each one dram, a dram of ſafron, mix them in a leaden morter.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:37512:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Pultis for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take marſh-mallow roots, three ounces, white lyllies an ounce, mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low leaves and henbane, each half an handful, dill ſeeds two drams, boil them ſoft and bruiſe them, add to them powder of the flowers of camomile and melilot, flower of linſeed &amp; fenegreek, each one ounce, oyl of ſeſamum, three ounces, ſafron a dram, make thereof a pultis.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers in the neck of the Womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take comfry roots, biſtort, each one ounce, leaves of planten, horſe-tayle, ſhepherds purſe, ſanacle, mous-ear— yarrow, each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, red roſe flowers half a handful, boyl them in a ſufficient quantity of water, and uſe the decoction for an injection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Cancer in the womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyl of violets five ounces, juice of ripe nightſhade berries four
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:37512:64"/>ounces, ceruſe waſhed two ounces, burnt lead waſhed, prepared tutia, each one ounce, frankinſenſe half an ounce, wax five ounces, mix them well in a leaden morter with a leaden peſtle, till they change colour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For inflamations in the womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inflamations in the womb are very dangerous, and oftentimes prove deadly to women with child, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore care muſt be uſed to apply apt remedies in the beginning of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper: if the heat be much, take of the leaves of ſengreen, purſlain lettice, planten, endive, nightſhade, water-lillies, vine leaves, <hi>Venus</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel-wort, of each of theſe half an handful, boyl them in ſharp wine till they be ſoft, then take and pound them, and add two ounces of barley meal, and two drams of bala ſtins, a dram of bole-armoniac, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle oyl of roſes, make it a pultis, and apply it to the region of the womb.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:37512:65"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An unguent for heat and inflama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take diachilon plaiſter two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the juice of <hi>Venus</hi> navel-wort, and planten, each half an ounce, oyl of roſes one ounce, <hi>Saccharum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turni</hi> a ſcrupple, work them in a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den morter into an ointment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Peſſary for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the juices of the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned plants, with the oyl of roſes, and the like, may be formed peſſaries very proper for this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Bath for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the forementioned herbs, and of mallows, marſh mallows, mugwort and fenegreek, of each what quantity you will; make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction thereof in a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of water, and let the patient ſit in it warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Injections for to cool the womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>New milk and roſe-water toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther injected into the womb with a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:37512:65"/>ſerringe have a good effect, or you may take leaves of planten, <hi>Venus</hi> navel-wort, water-lillies, and lettice, each one handful, red roſes, two pugils, boyl them in water, and add to the decoction an ounce of oyl of mirtles, and half an ounce of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and inject it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Rupture of the womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take wax, turpentine, gooſe greaſe and butter, each one dram, honey, deers ſuet, oyle of roſes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, ceruſe, tallow, each two drams, mix them and apply it inwardly in form of a peſſary, and outwardly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the parts with it, and apply it as a plaiſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For weakneſs of the womb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſeeds of wilde parſnips, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, anniſe, carrots, each one dram, roots of angelica and lovage, each half a dram, cloves, galanga, cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, each one dram and an half, make hereof a pouder, whereof take
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:37512:66"/>as much as will lye upon a groat morning and evening, in wine or any other liquor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For itching of the womb and privy parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have known ſome women ſo troubled with this malady, that they could ſeldom keep their hands from it; the truth is, this is an evil more troubleſom then dangerous. But for the cure:</p>
               <p>Take allom, nitre, and flower of brimſtone, each ſix drams, ſtaves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acre one ounce, work them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with vinegar of roſes and freſh butter into an ointment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with rub the place.</p>
               <p>Fine flower of brimſtone, and freſh butter unſalted, with the juice of a lemon wrought together into an ointment, will cure the itching alone, and is alſo excellent to kill crab-lice, and will cure the itch all over the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy if it be not too foul; then purging muſt be uſed with it.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:37512:66"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For grievous pains in the womb. A Gliſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take mercury, mugwort, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mint, penny-royal, each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, of the flowers of camomile and melilot, each half an handful, lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed and fenegreek each half an ounce, decoct them in fair water, and to a pint of the ſtrained liquor add of the electuary of <hi>hiaera ſimplex,</hi> and <hi>Benedict. laxativ.</hi> each half an ounce, oyl of water lillies two ounces, electuary of bay-berries half an ounce, and give it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An excellent pouder for all pains and gripings in the womb and umbili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take roots of angelica, maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, zedoary, each one dram, white dittany, anniſe-ſeeds, carrot-ſeeds, cumin-ſeeds, ſchoenanth, each half a dram, cloves and mace, each one ſcruple, ſugar the weight of them all, make it a pouder, whereof let
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:37512:67"/>the Patient take a dram at a time in wine, or any other convenient li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To drive down the termes an Electuary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the conſerves of betony, lavendar, balm, borrage, each one ounce, condited roots of pimper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, and condited orange-pill half an ounce, oyles of cynamon and fennel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, each three drops, make hereof an electuary with ſyrrup of mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To ſtay the overflowing of the Courſes, an Electuary</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take conſerve of red roſes two ounces, oak leaves; and tormentil, each one ounce, planten-ſeeds, and red corral, each one dram, <hi>Lapis haematis</hi> prepared half a ſcruple, with the juice of yarrow make it an Electuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A pouder to ſtop the Terms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take maſtick and red corral pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:37512:67"/>each one dram, pearls prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſmarage, each one ſcruple, amber and <hi>lapis haematis,</hi> each half a ſcruple, make it a fine pouder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the plague in the Guts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take anniſe-ſeeds, fennel, bay-berries, juniper-berries, tormentil, biſtort, balauſtins, pomgranate pills, each one ounce, roſe leaves, a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, boyle them in milk, ſtrain it, and add the yolk of an egg, ſix grains of <hi>Laudanum</hi> diſſolved in the ſpirit of mint, prepare it for a gliſter, and give it warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame accompanied with a violent looſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a pint of red wine, fountain-water a pint, cynamon bruiſed one ounce, boyl them till half be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, then take three new-laid eggs boyled very hard, take out the yolks and beat them very fine with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, ſtrain it, and drink warm three ſpoonfuls every hour.</p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:37512:68"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An hyſterick plaiſter for fits of the Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take <hi>Agnus</hi> caſtus-ſeeds a dram and an half, of all the kindes of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, each one dram and an half, white roſes in pouder one dram, gum <hi>Tacamahaca</hi> a dram, musk three grains, turpentine, wax, and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſufficient to make it a plaiſter, which ſpread and apply to the belly upon the region of the womb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A pouder for the Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take carrot-ſeeds, cumin and wild parſnip-ſeeds, each one dram, make it into pouder, whereof give a dram at a time upon the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Electuary for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take conſerve of marjoram, of roſemary-flowers, bugloſs, each two ounces, treacle, mithridate, each two drams, ſpecies of diacinin, and diamoſch. each one dram, ſyrrup of mugwort make it an electuary.</p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:37512:68"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>To procure eaſie delivery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſavin, <hi>Aristolochia</hi> the round, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ochis of mirrh caſtoreum, each one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ram, cinamon and root of aſſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acca, each half a dram, ſafron a ſcruple, give a dram at a time in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An excellent ſecret to help barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and procure eaſie deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take darnel and burn it, and let the woman receive the fume through a tunnel; and take barly meal, dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, mirrh, ſafron and frankinſenſe, and apply it pultis wiſe upon the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it helps conception, and procures eaſie delivery.</p>
               <p>The buds of the Sun-flower before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloſſome, boiled and eaten with butter, vinegar and pepper, do migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily excite to venery, and provoke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt more than the Artichoke.</p>
               <p>Nettle ſeeds are good for the ſame purpoſe; ſo is garden creſſes and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:37512:69"/>rocket, eaten with lettice and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaine.</p>
               <p>A peſſary made of the herb Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, and worn in the matrix, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the parts, comforts the womb, and ſtirs it up fit to conceive.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the white Feaver, Maids di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, or green ſickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is cauſed by obſtuction of the veſſels about the womb, when maids come to ripe age, and the natural ſeed begins to abound, exciting their deſires to joyn in fellowſhip with men, for want whereof the humors aſcend to the greater veins, and do ſtupifie the brain ſometimes to ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, moſt times to forgetfulneſs, and many times to raging madneſs, and do alſo vitiate the whole maſs of blood, which brings them to a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid complexion.</p>
               <p>This we muſt endeavour to help by Phyſick, when the maid cannot get her deſired cure.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:37512:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe pills for this purpoſe I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the maſſe of the Pill cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>hiera,</hi> with agarick one dram and an half, pills of opopanax three drams, extract of rubarb, centory the leſſe, gentian root, each one dram, ſteel prepared four drams, cuckow pintle root prepared, tartar vitriola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted each two ſcruples, Chymical oil of wormwood one ſcruple, oil of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon and cloves each ſix drops, ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup of the five opening roots, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to make it into a maſſe for Pills; of every dram hereof make ſix Pills, and let the patient take two every morning, and as many at four a Clock in the afternoon, drinking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it a draught of wormwood wine, or wormwood beer, and exerciſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it an hour.</p>
               <p>The leaves of hagtaper or mullen, which grows common enough in the Countrey, are good for maids to
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:37512:70"/>vvear in their ſhooes, to draw down their Courſes, the ſtopping vvhereof brings no ſmall evil unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To them that cannot ſo well ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low pills, I preſcribe ſome open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sirrups and Decoctions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An opening Decoction for the Green ſickneſs.</p>
               <p>Take roots of ſichory, madder and licorice clenſed, each half an ounce, annis and ſennel ſeeds each two drams, harts tongue one handful, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask roſes and borrage flowers, each half an handful, ſaffafras ſhaved thin one ounce, raiſins ſtoned one ounce and an half, cynamon halfe a dram, boyl them together in a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity of fountain vvater, until a third part be vvaſted, and let the patient drink thereof as often as ſhe pleaſes. To make it the more grateful to the taſte, you may ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en it with ſirrup of Lemons, or for vvant thereof ſuger may ſerve the turn.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:37512:70"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An opening and attennating Sirrup for the Green ſickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the juice of ſuccory and mugwort, both clarified, each five ounces, of the before mentioned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction eight ounces, juice of barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries four ounces, ſuger candy one pound, make them a ſirrup, the doſe vvhereof may be every morning two ounces, vvith three ounces of cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvater.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Electuary for the Green ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tak juice of Elder berries boiled to a juſt conſiſtence vvith ſuger, which the Apothecaries call Rob, four ounces, bay berries dried and powdered one ounce, two nutmegs, burnt harts horn one dram, <hi>ſpecies dearrhod.</hi> four ſcruples, vvhite am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber half a ſcruple, ſirrup of cichory one ounce and an half, ſo mix them vvell together into a ſoft Electuary, vvhereof ſhe may take the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:37512:71"/>of a nutmeg twice or thrice a day.</p>
               <p>Capers and broom buds are good for them to eat with their meat that are troubled with this diſtemper.</p>
               <p>There are outward means alſo to be uſed for the green ſickneſs, as oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and plaiſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An ointment for the Green ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oil of ſpiknard, and of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter almonds each two ounces, juice of mugwort an ounce, vineger half an ounce, ſet it on the fire till the moiſture be conſumed, and add to it in powder ſpiknard, ſquinanth and aſſarabacca root each one dram, and with a little wax make a liniment of it, wherewith anoint the region of the liver, and the parts about the vvomb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or elſe uſe this Ointment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyl of ſweet almonds and capers, of camomile and dill, each
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:37512:71"/>two ounces, of orris and wormwood each one ounce and an half, of vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of roſes one ounce, juices of rue, alexanders and mint each one ounce and an half, boil them till the juices be conſumed, and then put to it powder of ſquinanth and ſpike, of each a dram, with ducks greaſe and a little wax make it an ointment, vvherewith anoint the region of the Liver, the womb, and all the privy parts, rubbing it vvell about the lips and mouth of the ſame, and then uſe this plaiſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A plaister for the Green ſickneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take camomile, melilot, ſouthern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, ground-pine each one ounce, parſly ſeeds, tops of vvormwood, flowers of the leſſer centory, each two drams, powder them all, and take one dram of ſpike diſſolved in <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> and with a little oil of marjoram and roſes, and a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity of vvax, make it a
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:37512:72"/>plaiſter, which lay on the region of the Liver.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſuch as cannot hold their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take hogs and ſheeps bladders, hares ſtones, cocks throats, each half an ounce, acorns two ſcruples, leaver of nepp and mace, each one ſcruple, make it a powder, whereof give half a dram at a time in vvater of Oake leaves.</p>
               <p>The ſtones of bores, and the claws dried to powder and given, are very good for this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Alſo Diacinamom; and Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe drunk in wine is commended, calamints, mints, acorn cups, burnt ivory, mace, gum, arabick, and oak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en bark applyed hot to the <hi>peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Plaiſter for ſuch as cannot hold their water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take frankinſenſe one ounce, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum, maſtich, burnt ivory, acorn
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:37512:72"/>cups, each three drams, lignum, aloes and cinamon, each one dram, ſtyrax calamita, two drams, juice of mints four ounces, wax enough to make it a plaiſter, ſpread this plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter upon linnen or leather, and lay it above the privy members upon the place where the hair grows, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gods as far as the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="149-200" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <hi>For the <hi>French</hi> Pox an excellent method.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt begin vvith a purging potion.</p>
               <p>Take of the decoction of tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rind ſix ounces, which infuſe ſix hours upon hot coals, ſene half an ounce, rubarb two drams, hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dactills half a dram, caſſia new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn out of the canes one ounce.</p>
               <p>Let it boil a wlam or two at the end of the infuſion, ſtraine it, and add to the liuqor confectio hamec, elect. cariocoſtinum, each
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:37512:73"/>one dram and an half, ſpirit of tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine half a ſcruple, and let the patient take it faſting, keep vvarm after it, and take poſſet drink as it works.</p>
               <p>Then after a day or two take of the maſſe of the pills of fumitory, aurea, each one dram, pill cochie two drams, meercurius dulcis three drams, roſin of jollap two ſcruples, ſpirit of turpentine ſix drops, and vvith conſerve of vvormwood a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, make it into forty Pills, vvhereof take three at a time every other day.</p>
               <p>Then proceed to Dyet drink, which make thus:</p>
               <p>Take <hi>Lignum vitae</hi> eight ounces, bark of the ſame two ounces, ſaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fras one ounce, ſarſa parilla four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, liquorice two ounces, juniper berries one ounce, cynamon two drams, coriander ſeeds four drams, boil it in two gallons of vvater till
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:37512:73"/>one be conſumed, ſtrain it and drink it for an ordinary drink.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a foul running of the Reins, a poiſonous Clap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Prick-madam, one handful, quince ſeeds, rue, agnus caſtus, plantain each one ounce, tormentil roots half an ounce, red roſe flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers two pugils, vervaine one pugil, juice of Lemons ſix ounces, vvater of the tree mallow flowers one pint and an half; infuſe the herbs in the vvater four days, letting them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerate vvith the gentle heat of a bath, then ſtrain it, and reſerve it for uſe. The doſe is morning and evening three ſpoonfuls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Electuary for the Running of the Reins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take conſerve of red roſes, red corral prepared, harts horn pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared each one ſcruple, ballauſtins two ſcruples, mix them and take the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:37512:74"/>quantity of a nutmeg twice or thrice a day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Ointment for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyl of roſes, maſtich, and myrtles, each one ounce, balauſtins half a dram, with a little vvax, make it an unguent, wherewith anoint the privy members, and all the parts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them.</p>
               <p>If coldneſs of the members ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the diſtemper, then anoint the privy parts vvith oyl of vvorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, maſtich and mynts, and oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of marſh mallows; but if the yard and parts be over hot, waſh them vvith vvhites of eggs, planten vvater, and juice of lemons, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint them vvith oyl of water lillies; uſe alſo the vvater of the ſperme of frogs, and if the ſtones ſwell vvith heat, make a pultis vvith barley meal, oyl of lillyes, milk and ducks meat, and bind on the cods.</p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:37512:74"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cool and take away the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the matter in the Running of the Reins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of all the ſaunders oyl of vvater lillyes, the unguent popule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, juice of nightſhade each a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity, camphire half a ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, mix them vvell and bind them upon the genitals.</p>
               <p>If the flowing matter be vvatry and thin, then uſe ſuch things as are drying and ſtrengthning, and do help the digeſtive virtue of the ſtones, and correct the vvatrineſs of the ſeed, as ſpecies Aromatic. roſat. ſirrup of mints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To correct the watrineſs of ſeed in Gonorrhea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take mints and Roman vvorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvood each one handful, agnus ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus ſeeds, myrtle berries and roſe flowers, each two drams, boyl them in red vvine, and ſweeten it with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere; take it often.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:37512:75"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take old conſerve of red roſes one ounce and an half, amber and red corral prepared each one dram, cloves, mace, frankinſenſe, each one ſcruple, with ſirrup of myrtles make it an Electuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Or uſe this powder in red wine to thicken the ſeed, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the ſtones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take maſtich, frankinſenſe each one dram, amber half a dram, cory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander ſeeds two drams, vine leaves, mints each half a dram, ſugar of ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes one ounce, make it a fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers in the bladder or reins, cauſed by Venery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take polipody of the Oak, and licorice ſliced, each half an ounce, of the four greater cool ſeeds each one dram, violets and borrage flowers each two pugils, jujubes half an ounce, damask prunes an ounce, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:37512:75"/>half an ounce, ſena two ounces and an half, infuſe them one night in barly water, in the morning boil and ſtrain it, afterwards in a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity of the decoction diſſolve an ounce and an half of Manna, caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia new drawn three ounces, boil them to the thickneſs of an opiate, adding in the end half an ounce of rubarb in powder. The doſe is an ounce to be taken in the morning once a week.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers in the Bladder or Reins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of caſſia two ounces, manna one ounce, pulpe of ſebeſtins and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marinds each one ounce, of the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcilage of flea-wort ſix drams, of the four greater cool ſeeds, each one dram, juice of licorice two drams; with ſirrup of roſes ſolutive make it an opiate. The doſe is an ounce in a morning.</p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:37512:76"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Electuary for the French Pox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take guiacum wood finely pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and powder of ſarſaperrilla, each one ounce, ſpecies diatrion ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talon, and diarrhod. abbatis each two drams, conſerve of ſuchory ſix ounces; with ſirrup of ſuchory make in an Electuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers in the yard, cauſed by the Pox.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyl of ſweet almonds, oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of roſes each three ounces, wax an ounce, mercury precipitate half an ounce, mxi them for uſe. For the itching under the prepuce and the top of the yard, make a decoction vvith ducks meat and pomgranate pills, and waſh the place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To eaſe the grievous pains of the yard, got by a Clap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take mallows, marſh-mallows, linſeed, dill camomile flowers, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:37512:76"/>mellilot each a handful, boil them in vvater and foment the yard and ſtones vvith the liquor, then lay on the boiled herbs pultis vviſe upon the parts.</p>
               <p>The women may alſo uſe this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction for the ſame purpoſe, inje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it into the Matrix with a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe, and applying it pultice wiſe outwardly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A plaiſter for the stone in the Bladder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oil of ſpike, camomile and dill each ſix drams, oil of ſcorpions half an ounce, <hi>Ammoniacum, Bdelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> pitch diſſolved in vinegar each half an ounce, olibanum three drams, euphorbium one dram, incorporate them into a plaiſter, and apply it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bottom of the belly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A plaiſter for Caranles on the neck of the bladder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the beſt aloes two drams, ariſtolochia and mirrh each half a
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:37512:77"/>ſcruple, tutia prepared half a dram, liquid ſtyrax enough to make it a plaiſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A drink to cool the heat of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſeeds of poppy, lettice, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dive, and the four greater cool ſeeds each half an ounce, ſebeſtens in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſeven, boil them in a ſufficient quantity of water till half be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then ſtrain it, and in four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſtrained liquor diſſolve one ounce and an half of the ſirrup of water-lillyes, and give it for a doſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An outward application to cool the heat of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rin, and inflama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Bladder, Reins and privy members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the diſtilled water of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lillyes three ounces, of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of violets and houſe-leek each one ounce, juice of nightſhade and houſe-leek each one ounce, breſt-milk
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:37512:77"/>one ounce and an half, oyl of violets one ounce, mix them, and dip therein hot cloths and apply them wet upon the members underneath the cods, and above upon the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the belly.</p>
               <p>To mundifie unlcers in the bladder, and eaſe pains of them and in the yard, it is good to inject Cows milk warm with a Serringe, or you may take the water of milk diſtilled, with barly vvater and fine ſugar, and inject it into the yard vvith a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe.</p>
               <p>But to dry and conſolidate the Ulcer after it is clenſed, uſe this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoliative vvith a Serringe.</p>
               <p>take the whites of four eggs well beaten, to which add bole armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick and dragons blood each two ſcruples, muſcilage of flea-wort and womans milk each two ounces, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that which is to be powdered,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:37512:78"/>mingle all well together, and inject it with a Serringe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take alſo this Electuary to heal the pains of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take lohoch of poppy, diatrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canth, frigid. each half an ounce, bole armonick one dram, pouder the bole armonick very finely, mix it, and make an electuary with a little ſirrup of violets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of Piſſing Blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This generally proceeds from Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the reins and bladder, and ſometimes is cauſed by falls, blows and bruiſes; ſometimes cleer blood is avoided, and ſometimes blood mixed with corruption; ſometimes watry blood, and ſometimes blood like ſtinking clots of fleſh.</p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:37512:78"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Ointment for piſſing blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oyl of mirtles and roſes each ſix drams, balauſtins, pomgranate pills, ſiumach, bole armonick each two ſcruples, pouder what is to be poudred, and with a little wax make it an unguent, wherewith anoint the reins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Potion for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of violets, myrtles each ſix ounces, waters of planten, purſlain and endive each twelve ounces, mix them, and drink hereof often.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cure a Priapiſmus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Priapiſm is an immoderate and continual erection and ſtanding of the Yard, without any deſire or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to venery, or ejection of ſeed, wherein it differs from another paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:37512:79"/>of the yard called Satyria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, in which there is, beſides the ſtanding of the yard, a coiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and emiſſion of the ſeed with pleaſure.</p>
               <p>In the cure hereof the patient muſt be careful to avoid ſuch things as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and increaſe windineſs, and to uſe ſuch things as diſſolve and break wind, outwardly foment the yard with this fomentation.</p>
               <p>Take penny royal, origany, each half an handful, carawayes, ameos, anni-ſeeds, fennel-ſeeds, cumyn-ſeeds each two drams, boyl them in a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity of water till half be conſumed, then dip in it a ſpong, and therewith foment the yard.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cure the continual ſtanding of the yard, proceeding from too much heat of the gential members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this caſe the patient muſt ſhun
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:37512:79"/>all ſuch things as ingender heat, and uſe cold things: It is very good to hold the yard in cold water, and to anoint the root of the yard with cool oyls, as with oyl of roſes, water-lillyes, and a little vinegar.</p>
               <p>It is good alſo to wear a plate of lead, vvith a hole through it, for to put the yard thorow upon the pecten above the yard, and let it come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath, fitting it to the place.</p>
               <p>Vomiting is likewiſe proper for this diſtemper, but not Purging.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A gentle vomit, working without harm, which I alwayes uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take an ounce of aſſarabacca roots, boyl them in a pint of water till half be conſumed, then ſtrain it, put to it two ounces of ſimple oxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, and giveit for a vomit; but before the patient takes the vomit, take a hen and boil her, making
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:37512:80"/>cleer broth, and having the broth in readineſs, about a quarter of an hour after the patient hath taken the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, let him drink a draught of the broth, and ſo drink between every vomit until it hath done working. Thoſe that cannot get hen broth, may uſe cleer poſſet drink in ſtead of it.</p>
               <p>In the diſtemper of a Priapiſme, let the patient be ſure to abſtain from wine and diuretick medecines, and apply to the loyns and privy members this Pultis following:</p>
               <p>Take nightſhade, purſlain, lettice, water lillyes, boil them in water till they be tender, then pound them, and apply them hot to the privy members.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Feavers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To cure a Sanguine Feaver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of endive an ounce
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:37512:80"/>and an half, of bugloſs half an ounce, waters of lupines, endive and bugloſs each an ounce, mix it, and take it in the morning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another digeſtive in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a Feaver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of wood-ſorrel an ounce and an half, ſirrup of endive half an ounce, diſtilled water of prunes, endive and ſorrel, each one ounce, mingle them, and take there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of at twice.</p>
               <p>The diſtilled water of prunes I have alwayes uſed with excellent ſucceſs in moſt Juleps for all Feavers, which you may eaſily prepare and keep by you, to be ready upon all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
               <p>Take prunes what quantity you pleaſe, bruiſe them and diſtil them in a common ſtill: And at any time, when occaſion requires, you may
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:37512:81"/>give of this water alone with a little ſugar, if you have nothing elſe to add with it.</p>
               <p>But uſually I prepare it thus:</p>
               <p>Take prune water four ounces, juice of oranges two ounces, ſirrup of gilliflowers two ounces, a few drops of ſpirit of vitriol, mix it, and let the patient drink two or three ſpoonfuls at a time.</p>
               <p>You may likewiſe keep juice of oranges at all times in readineſs by you; taking good ſtore of oranges when they are moſt plenty, and preſs out their juice, claryfie it, and put it in a glaſs veſſel with a tap hole at the bottom, and cover over the juice about an inch thick at the top with ſallet oyl, ſo you may preſerve your juice freſh as long as you pleaſe, drawing it out at the bottom when you have occaſion to uſe it.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of a Feaver have a ſpecial regard to the conſtitution of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:37512:81"/>the body; if the body be pletho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, or if blood or choller abound, let your principal remedy be blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letting; vomiting, and cliſters alſo are very proper: Then give ſuch things as cool the heat, as fair water with the juice of lemons, barberris, currans, pomgranates or quinces.</p>
               <p>The diſtilled waters of endive, purſlain, ſuccory, ſorrel, ſtrawber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, borage, bugloſs, violets, roſes, with which you may mix any of the ſirrups of the ſame herbs, flowers or juices.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of Feavers the conſerve of wood-ſorrel taken with <hi>Diaſcordium</hi> mixed together, is of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe; you may take of the ſame conſerve an ounce, <hi>diaſcordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> a dram, mix them and take it at twice; or you may take the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and ſharpen it with oyl of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, and eat it at any time againſt thirſt.</p>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:37512:82"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>This following Sudorifick is with good ſucceſs given in the beginning of Feavers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take water of cichory and elder flowers each equal parts, in which infuſe harts-horn burnt and poudred a dram and an half, ſtrain it, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve in the liquor ſirrup of fumitory an ounce, juice of citrons two ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, ſalt of wormwood one ſcruple, Bezoar ſtone eight grains, mix it and give it in the morning faſting, warm, to provoke ſweat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Outwardly uſe this Epithema to the region of the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take roſe water three ounces, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and bugloſs water each two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vinegar of roſes half an ounce, juice of Lemons two drawms, red ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders one dram, lignum aloes, half a
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:37512:82"/>dram. Dip linnen cloths herein and apply them to the region of the heart, and anoint the reins with oyl of roſes and violets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a putrid Feaver, a Bolus to open the Belly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take caſſia, manna, pulpe of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marinds each halfa dram, oyl of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeeds three grains, diagryd, four grains; give them for a Bolus.</p>
               <p>It is very proper in this caſe alſo, to give a Cliſter; which prepare thus:</p>
               <p>Take leaves of mallows, violets, pellitory, mercury, camomile flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers each one handful, pearl barley, half an handful, boil them in a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity of water, and in ſix ounces of the colature diſſolve caſſia one ounce, ſirrup of roſes ſolutive half an ounce, oyl of violets or roſes two ounces, the yolk of an egg and a
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:37512:83"/>little ſalt, mix them for a Cliſter and put it up.</p>
               <p>After the body is thus lenified, forthwith have recourſe to blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letting, as the moſt neceſſary and beſt remedy; afterwards if the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient be very dry, give him a Julep with prune water, ſorrel water, and juice of lemons and oranges, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of vitriol.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Emulſion to cauſe reſt in Feavers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the decoction of ſaſſafras four ounces, two dates ſtoned, boyl and ſtrain them, and to the liqor add an ounce of white poppy ſeeds bruiſed, half an ounce of gourd ſeeds, and ſweeten it with ſirrup of wild poppy flowers.</p>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:37512:83"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Cordial Potion</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take water of borage and bugloſs powers each five ounces, cynamon water half an ounce, ſirrup of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons and citrons each an ounce, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies liberant a dram, diamag, frig, a ſcruple, give hereof a draught warm three or four times an hour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Quotidian Feaver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take manna an ounce and an half, and diſſolve it in hen broth, adding a little mace, ſtrain it and drink it uſing it many dayes together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Chollerick bodies uſe this following Potion, in a quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, tertian, or quartan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take damask prunes in number ten, tamarinds an ounce, ſebeſtins
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:37512:84"/>jujubes each in number ten, raiſins an ounce and an half, five dates, flowers of violets, borage and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleſs each one pugil, gourd ſeeds half an ounce, decoct theſe in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity of water and in the decoction infuſe rubarb a dram and an half, myrobalans citrine two drams, ginger one ſcruple, ſtrain it and put to it an ounce of ſolutive ſirrup of roſes, and give it the patient in the morning warm.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In quartain Feavers, an excellent Potion to purg by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the five opening roots each half an ounce, <hi>Carduus benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> harts-tongue, tops of worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood each one handful, flowers of borage, bugloſs, violets, roſes, each half a handful, flowers of the leſſer centory a pugil, ſena half an ounce, rubarb three drams, citron and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:37512:84"/>pills each one dram, cynamon half a dram, diagrid. ſix grains.</p>
               <p>Let theſe be all cut and ſliced ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall, and then tyed up in a fine linnen cloth or bag, which infuſe in white-wine, and let the patient drink thereof every morning faſting a good draught.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For quartain Feavers, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy bodies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take ſirrup of violets, bugloſs, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and fumitory each one ounce; waters of purſlain, fumitory harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue, borage, bugloſs each one ounce and an half, make it a Julep for three doſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Decoction provoking Sweat and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rin, good in tertian Feavers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take roots of parſley, ſparagus,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:37512:85"/>Kneeholm, nettles each one ounce, orris, elecampane each half an ounce, twelve bayberries, flowers of camo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, tops of dill each a pugil, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mint, penny-royal each half a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſeeds of comin, annis, fennel, and citrons each one dram, decoct all in a good quantity of water, and let the patient drink of it often.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a burning Feaver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the diſtilled waters of cicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſorrel, wild poppey, betony each one ounce and an half, rasberry wine one ounce, ſirrup of the juice of citrons, lemons, barberrieseach half an ounce, yellow ſanders half a dram, give of it often three or four ſpoonfulls at a time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For a Hectick Feaver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To keep the belly open take of the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:37512:85"/>decoction of pruins four ounces, wherein diſſolve manna an ounce, let them be ſo hot as to boyl up, then ſtrain it, and drink the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Afterwards for the Hectick, uſe this Electuary every day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take conſerve of roſes and violets each half an ounce, caſſia newly drawen and boyled up with ſugar five drams, ſpecies Aromat. roſat. half a dram, chymical oyl of anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds three grains, temper it together for an Electuary; it will keep open the belly, and ſtrengthen the heart, brain, and liver.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Peſtilence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the time of the Plague it is good for preſervation to uſe fumigations, which you may prepare after this manner:</p>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:37512:86"/>
               <p>Take red roſes, mirtles, citron citron pills, all the ſaunders of each two drams, mirrh, ſtorax, calamita, gum dragon, gum arabick each one dram, camphire a ſcruple, a little musk, diſſolve the gums in roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and vinegar, mix and work them all together into a maſs, and form little rolls or troches of them, which being dryed, you may carry about you, and burn of them upon coals when you have occaſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pills to be uſed in Plague time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take aloes ſix drams, mirrh three drams, ſafron one dram, rubarb two drams, agarick trochiſcated one dram, zcloves edoary, ſeeds of citrons peeled each one ſcruple, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron dill half a dram, tormenti roots, red ſaunders each a dram and an half, oriental bole waſhed and prepared two drams, camphire half a
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:37512:86"/>ſcruple; reduce all theſe into a fine powder, and with the ſirrup of the juice of citrons make them into a maſs, of which form pills of the bigneſs of a peaſe. The doſe is four Pills in a morning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To comfort the Spirits, let the ſick drink often of this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Julep.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take waters of endive, ſorrel, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, bugloſs, balm each equal parts, ſeeds and pills of citrons each two drams, harts-horn burnt and prepared five drams, boyl them gently, ſtrain it, and to the cola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture add ſirrup of citrons, juice of currans each equal parts, make it a Julep, adding a little cinamon water, and let the Patient drink of it often.</p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:37512:87"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Sweating Potion to be given in the beginning of the diſeaſe as ſoon as one is infected with the Plague.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take tormentil roots, white dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, red coral, bole armonick pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, terra ſigillata, each one dram, gentian root, vervaine each one dram and an half, ſafron a ſcruple, make all theſe into a powder, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of take one dram, treacle half an ounce, ſirrup of ſcabious and mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort each one ounce and an half, water of <hi>Carduus Benedictus,</hi> four ounces, mix it, and give it the ſick party warm, and let him go to bed and ſweat well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Electuary for the Plague, to be taken every day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take juice of ſcabious, ſcordium,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:37512:87"/>
                  <hi>Carduus Benedictus</hi> each two drams, Andromachus treacle three drams, citron ſeeds blanched a dram and an half, with ſirrup of the juice of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berryes a ſufficient quantity, over a gentle fire, make it into an Electu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, whereof let the ſick party take a dram at a time, more or leſs, as you find the operation of it: endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſweat upon it, and continue provoking ſweat with <hi>Carduus</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet drink, according as the patients ſtrength can bear it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This following cauſes ſweat, and abates the ſenſe of the parts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the beſt treacle a dram, ſirrup of wild poppy flowers one ounce, give it in two ounces of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duus</hi> water.</p>
               <p>In all diſeaſes whatſoever, labour to ſhun all vehement affections of the mind, as Angar and Sorrow, and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:37512:88"/>ſtedfaſtly ſix your hope upon our Heavenly Father, the Great Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, deſpiſing the World, in reſpect of him who <hi>worketh all things for the beſt to them that fear him.</hi> Uſe his Means with praiſe and thankſgiving, and patiently wait for his bleſſing upon them. To whom be all Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory, for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Plaiſter to reſolve cold and windy tumors in the J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ynts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take oil of dill half a pound, roſin of the pine tree two pound, common roſin three pounds, new wax one pound, the powders of comin and barberries of each one pound, melt what is to be melted, and then ſtrain it, and put in your powders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the bitting of a mad Dog.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take galbanum, opopanax, ſaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penum
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:37512:88"/>each half a dram, euphorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, florentine, orris, ariſtolochia the round, gentian roote each one dram, crawfiſh ſhell, two drams, wax ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, turpentine two ounces, mix them for a plaiſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Plaiſter for poiſoned wounds, bitings, and stingings of Serpents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take barberry meal and bean meal, each ten drams, licoras, marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallow roots, pitch, each five ounces, white-wax and gooſe-greaſe each ten ounces, incorporate them with old oil and urin of a maid child ſufficient for a plaiſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Plaiſter for the ſwelling of the Cods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take Bdelium, opopanax, ſaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onum diſſolved in vineger, each
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:37512:89"/>half an ounce, muſcilage of marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, linſeede and fenegreeke each two drams and an half, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of camomile and melilot each three drams, beam meal three ounces butter half an ounces; with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of figs and mallows, make it a plaiſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Plaiſter to ripen Venereous Buboes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take mallow and violet leaves, each two handfuls, roots of marſh mallows half a pound, white lilly heads four ounces, boil them in a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity of water, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them ſmall, adding thereunto whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and barly meal each a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, common oil and butter ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> three ounces, hogs-lard two ounce and an half, the yolks of two e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> mix them for a plaiſters.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37512:89"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
